-== 派拉蒙电影公司 1972年出品 ==-
-== 教父 第一部 ==-
-== The Godfather Part I  ==-
我相信美国
I believe in America.
美国使我发了财
America has made my fortune.
And I raised my daughter in the American fashion.
而我以美国方式教养我的女儿
我给她自由
I gave her freedom, but I taught her never to dishonour her family.
但也告诉她永远不要有辱家门
She found a boyfriend, not an Italian.
她交了位男友但不是意大利人
She went to the movies with him. She stayed out late.
她跟他去看电影，深夜才回家
我并没有责骂她
I didn't protest.
两个月前他与另一个男孩
Two months ago he took her for a drive with another boyfriend.
带她去兜风
They made her drink whiskey
他们强灌她喝威士忌
然后他们想要占她便宜
and then they tried to take advantage of her.
She resisted, she kept her honour.
她抵抗，她保住了名节
于是他们像对动物般的毒打她
So they beat her like an animal.
When I went to the hospital, her nose was broken,
当我到医院时
她的鼻梁断了
她的下巴被打碎了
her jaw was shattered, held together by wire.
必须用钢丝绑着才不会掉下来
She couldn't even weep because of the pain.
她痛得不能哭
But I wept. Why did I weep?
但我却哭了，我为什么哭呢？
She was the light of my life.
我视她如珠如宝
Beautiful girl.
长得很美丽
Now she will never be beautiful again.
现在她再也美丽不起来
Sorry.
不好意思
I went to the police, like a good American.
我…像个守法的美国人一样
我去报警
These two boys were brought to trial.
那两个男孩受到了审判
法官判他们有期徒刑三年 但缓刑
The judge sentenced them to three years in prison, but suspended the sentence.
Suspended the sentence! They went free that very day!
缓刑！
他们当天就没事了！
I stood in the courtroom like a fool.
我像个傻瓜似的站在法庭中
Those two bastards, they smiled at me.
而那两个混蛋竟朝着我笑
Then I said to my wife, "For justice, we must go to Don Corleone."
于是我对我太太说
为求公道 我们必须去找柯里昂阁下
你去报警前为何不先来找我？
Why did you go to the police? Why didn't you come to me first?
What do you want of me? Tell me anything, but do what I beg you to do.
你要我怎么样？
你尽管吩咐 但求你一定要帮我这个忙
What is that?
帮你什么忙？
I want them dead.
That I cannot do.
那个我办不到
I'll give you anything you ask.
你要什么，我都会给你
I've known you many years, but this is the first time you've asked for help.
我们相识多年
这是你第一次来找我帮忙
I can't remember the last time you invited me for a cup of coffee.
我记不起你上次是何时 请我到你家去喝咖啡了
Even though my wife is godmother to your only child.
何况我太太 还是你独生女的教母
But let's be frank here. You never wanted my friendship.
我坦白说吧！
你从来就不想要我的友谊
And you were afraid to be in my debt.
而且你怕欠我人情
I didn't want to get into trouble.
我不想卷入是非
I understand.
我了解
You found Paradise in America.
你在美国发了财
You made a good living, had police protection and there were courts of law.
生意做的很好，生活过的很好
有警察和法律保护你
You didn't need a friend like me.
你不需要我这种朋友
But now you come to me and say,
但是…
现在你来找我说
柯里昂阁下，请帮我主持公道
"Don Corleone, give me justice."
But you don't ask with respect.
但你对我一点尊重也没有
You don't offer friendship. You don't even think to call me Godfather.
你并不把我当朋友
你甚至不愿意喊我教父
You come on my daughter's wedding day and ask me to murder for money.
你在我女儿结婚当天来我家
用钱收买我为你杀人
我只是要求你主持公道
I ask you for justice.
那不是公道，你女儿还活着
That is not justice. Your daughter is alive.
Let them suffer, then, as she suffers.
那么让他们像她一样受折磨
我应该付你多少钱？
How much shall I pay you?
包纳萨拉
Bonasera, Bonasera.
到底我做了什么
What have I ever done to make you treat me so disrespectfully?
让你这么的不尊重我
If you'd come in friendship,
如果你以朋友身分来找我
the scum that ruined your daughter would be suffering this very day.
那么伤害你女儿的杂碎 就会受到折磨
And if an honest man like you should make enemies, they'd be my enemies.
你这种诚实人的敌人
也就是我的敌人
And then they would fear you.
那么，他们就会怕你
Be my friend?
当我的朋友？
Godfather?
教父
Good.
很好
Some day, and that day may never come, I'll ask a service of you.
他日我或需要你的帮忙
也可能不会有那么一天
But until that day...
但在那一天到来之前
...accept this justice as a gift on my daughter's wedding day.
收下这份公道 做为小女结婚之礼
- Grazie, Godfather. - Prego.
-谢谢，教父 -别客气
这件事交给…克里曼沙
Give this to Clemenza.
I want people that aren't going to get carried away.
我要用可靠的人 头脑清醒的人
We're not murderers, in spite of what this undertaker says.
我们不是谋杀犯，下手别太重
- Where's Michael? - Don't worry, he'll be here.
-麦克在哪？ -别担心，他一会就来
没有麦克我不照相
We're not taking the picture without Michael.
待会再拍
- What's the matter? - It's Michael.
-什么事？ -麦克的事
Don Barzini.
你好，巴西尼阁下
你认得我儿子吧？
保利，让我喝点酒
Hey, Paulie! Let me have some wine.
保利，再来点酒
Paulie! More wine.
- You look terrific on the floor. - Are you a dance judge or something?
-你看起来棒极了 -你是裁判还是什么？
闪开吧，到附近晃晃 做你的工作
Take a walk and do your job.
Sandra, watch the kids. Don't let them run wild.
仙杜拉，帮个忙 别让孩子乱跑，好吗？
你看好你自己，好吗？
You watch yourself, all right?
20, 30 grand. In small bills, cash.
两三万元小钞，全是现金
In that little silk purse.
全在那个小丝袋里
If this were somebody else's wedding... Sfortunato!
如果这是我的婚礼我就发财了
Hey, Paulie!
保利，接住吧！
Stupid jerk!
你这个笨蛋！
What's the matter?
怎么回事？
- Have to go back to work. - Tom.
-我得回去工作了 -汤姆
这是婚礼的一部分
No Sicilian can refuse any request on his daughter's wedding day.
没有西西里人在女儿结婚那天 能拒绝任何的请求
柯里昂阁下 能受邀到贵府深感荣幸
Don Corleone, I'm honoured and grateful that you have invited me.
你们在干什么？滚！
Get out of here! It's a private party. Go on!
这是私人宴会，快滚
What is it? It's my sister's wedding.
这算什么？是我妹妹的婚礼
Goddamn FBI don't respect nothing!
该死的联邦密探什么都不尊重
Come here, come here, come here!
过来这！…
...but towards the end, he was paroled to help with the American war effort,
但最后他获假释去为美国作战
过去六个月 他在我的糕饼店做事
so for six months he's worked in my pastry shop.
Nazorine, what can I do for you?
纳色利，我的朋友 我能为你做什么？
现在战争结束了
Now that the war is over,
这男孩，安索 他们要把他遣返意大利
this boy, Enzo, they want to repatriate him back to Italy.
Godfather, I have a daughter. You see, she and Enzo...
教父，我有个女儿 她和安索…
You want Enzo to stay in this country, and your daughter to be married.
你要安索留在这个国家 和你女儿成亲
你什么都了解，谢谢
You understand everything.
Mr Hagen. Thank you.
哈金先生，谢谢
待会看看我为你女儿 做的结婚蛋糕
Wait till you see the wedding cake I made for your daughter!
这么高…还有一对新人和天使
The bride, the groom and the angel...
- Who should I give this job to? - Not to our paisa.
这件事我该交给谁去办？
别给我们这个选区
Give it to a Jew Congressman in another district. Who else is on the list?
给别地区的犹太籍众议员
名单上还有谁？
你好！麦克！
Hey, Michael!
He's not on the list, but Luca Brasi wants to see you.
路卡布拉西不在名单上 但他想要见你
Is this necessary?
这个…有这个必要吗？
He didn't expect to be invited to the wedding, so he wanted to thank you.
他没料到会受邀参加婚礼 所以要向你致谢
好吧
柯里昂阁下，在令媛婚礼这天
Don Corleone, I'm honoured and grateful that you have invited me
能受邀到贵府深感荣幸
on the wedding day of your daughter. May their first child be a masculine child.
希望他们早生贵子
麦克！
Michael...
那边的那个人在自言自语
That man over there is talking to himself.
See that scary guy over there?
看到那边 那个吓人的砘锪寺穑
- He's a very scary guy. - What's his name?
-他很叫人害怕 -他是谁？叫什么名字？
His name is Luca Brasi. He helps my father out sometimes.
他叫做路卡布拉西 有时候替家父办事
Michael, he's coming over here!
麦克！等一下，他过来了
麦克！
汤姆！
You look terrific!
你气色好极了！
家兄汤姆哈金，这是凯亚当斯
My brother Tom Hagen, Miss Kay Adams.
-你好 -你好
你父亲要见你
Your father's been asking for you.
- Very nice to meet you. - Nice to meet you.
-幸会！ -幸会
Why does your brother have a different name?
若他是你哥哥，为何不同姓？
小时候在街上 发现汤姆无家可归
My brother Sonny found Tom Hagen in the street.
He had no home, so my father took him in.
所以家父收养了他
He's been with us ever since.
从此他就和我们住在一起了
He's a good lawyer.
他是个好律师
不是西西里人 但我想他会当军师
Not a Sicilian. I think he's going to be consigliere.
- What's that? - That's a...
-那是什么？ -那是…
...like a counsellor, an advisor. Very important for the family.
像是个顾问 在家族中的地位非常重要
You like your lasagne?
你的扁形通心面还好吧？
柯里昂阁下
Don Corleone.
在令媛的婚礼受到邀请
I'm honoured and grateful
that you have invited me to your daughter's wedding.
深感荣幸与感激
On the day of your daughter's wedding.
在令媛结婚的当天
And I hope that their first child will be a masculine child.
我希望他们能早生贵子
I pledge my ever-ending loyalty.
这是我一点小小的心意
-祝福他们俩白头偕老 -谢谢你，路卡
- For your daughter's bridal purse. - Thank you, Luca. Most valued friend.
我最珍贵的朋友
Don Corleone, I'm going to leave you now, because I know you're busy.
柯里昂阁下，我晓得你忙 我先告退了
Thank you.
谢谢
Signora Corleone!
柯里昂夫人
No!
不！…
Senator Cauley apologised for not coming, but said you'd understand.
科利参议员对不能亲自来致歉
他说你会谅解的
Also some of the judges. They've all sent gifts.
还有一些法官也一样 他们都送了礼物
敬你！
What is that outside?
外面是怎么回事？
强尼！…
Johnny! Johnny!
I love you!
我爱你！
他大老远由加州赶来参加婚礼
He came all the way from California. I told you he'd come!
我告诉过你他会来的
已经两年了，他也许又有麻烦
- He's probably in trouble again. - He's a good godson.
他是个好教子
Johnny, Johnny! Sing a song!
强尼！…唱首歌
You never said you knew Johnny Fontane!
麦克！你从未告诉我 你认得强尼方亭
-你想见他吗？ -当然！
- Sure. You want to meet him? - Great! Sure.
- My father helped him with his career. - He did?
-家父帮他建立他的事业 -真的？
How?
怎么做的？
- Let's listen to this song. - Michael...
-我们先听这首唱 -不，麦克
Please, Michael. Tell me.
拜托，麦克！告诉我
When Johnny was starting out, he was signed to a personal service contract
强尼刚出道时 和一个乐队领班签了合约
with a big bandleader.
当他走红后，想要解除合约
And as his career got better and better, he wanted to get out of it.
强尼是家父的教子
Johnny is my father's godson.
My father went to see this bandleader.
于是家父去见乐队负责人
He offered him 10,000 dollars to let Johnny go,
而且出一万元要他与强尼解约
but the bandleader said no.
他说不行！
So the next day my father went to see him, but this time with Luca Brasi.
第二天家父再去见他 只是这次带着路卡布拉西
Within an hour,
一个小时之内
he signed a release for a certified cheque of 1,000 dollars.
他签了解约书 只收了一千元的支票
- How did he do that? - Made him an offer he couldn't refuse.
他是怎么办到的？
家父提了个他不能拒绝的条件
那是什么？
- What was that? - Luca Brasi held a gun to his head,
路卡布拉西用枪顶着他的头
他要是不签字脑袋就会开花
and father said that either his brains or his signature would be on the contract.
That's a true story.
这是真实的故事
That's my family, Kay. It's not me.
凯，那是我的家庭，不是我
Beautiful!
我会处理的
I'll take care of it.
汤姆！
Tom...
I want you to find Santino. Tell him to come to the office.
叫山提诺来我的办公室
How are you, Fredo?
你好吗？弗雷多
-家兄弗雷多 -这位是凯亚当斯
My brother Fredo, this is Kay Adams.
- Hi. - How are you doing?
-你好 -你好吗？
- This is my brother Mike. - Are you having a good time?
-这是舍弟麦克 -玩的愉快吗？
Yeah. This is your friend?
这是你的朋友？
I don't know what to do. My voice is weak. It's weak.
我不知道该怎么办
我的嗓子很虚弱，很虚弱
Anyway, if I had this part in the picture, it puts me right back on top again.
总之我若能得到那部戏的角色
我会再次走红的
But this... man won't give it to me, the head of the studio.
但是电影公司的老板不让我演
-他叫什么名字？ -华尔斯
- What's his name? - Woltz.
He won't give it to me, and he says there's no chance.
他不肯让我演 而且还说门都没有
Sonny?
山尼？
- Sonny, are you in there? - What?
山尼？你在里面吗？
什么事？
The old man wants you.
老头子要见你
好，马上去
One minute.
山尼
一个月以前
A month ago he bought the movie rights to this book, a best-seller.
他买下这本畅销书的电影版权
The main character is a guy just like me.
男主角就像是我的写照
我根本不需要演 只要当我自己即可
I wouldn't even have to act.
但…教父，我不知该怎么办？
Godfather, I don't know what to do.
你要表现得像个男人！
You can act like a man! What's the matter with you?
你是怎么回事？
这就是你在好莱坞学到的？
Is this how you turned out a Hollywood finocchio, that cries like a woman?
哭的像个女人？
该怎么办？怎么办？
"What can I do? What can I do?" What is that nonsense?
算什么鬼话？
Ridiculous.
岂有此理！
- You spend time with your family? - Sure I do.
-你有花时间与家人共聚吗？ -我当然有
Good.
很好
Because a man who doesn't spend time with his family can never be a real man.
因为不抽空陪家人的男人 不是真正的男人
过来这
You look terrible. I want you to eat.
你看来糟透了，我要你多吃点
好好休息
Rest, and in a month this Hollywood big shot will give you what you want.
从现在起一个月内 好莱坞大亨会让你愿望成真
It's too late, they start shooting in a week.
太迟了 他们一周内就要开拍了
I'm going to make him an offer he can't refuse.
我会给他一个 他无法拒绝的提议
现在你到外面去好好的玩
Just go outside and enjoy yourself, and forget about all this nonsense.
-其他的交给我来办 -好的
- I want you to leave it all to me. - All right.
- What time does my daughter leave? - Soon, after they cut the cake.
我女儿女婿何时离开？
切完蛋糕后的几分钟
Do we give your son-in-law something important?
你的新女婿要给重要职务吗？
Never. Give him a living, but never discuss the family business with him.
永远不要！
让他们过好日子 但别让他插手家族中的事
- What else? - Virgil Sollozzo called.
还有什么事？
威尔斯索拉索来过电话
- We'll have to see him next week. - When you come back from California.
下周我们必须安排跟他见面
等你从加州回来我们再讨论
- When am I going to California? - Tonight.
我何时要去加州了？
我要你今晚去
I want you to talk to this movie big shot and settle this business for Johnny.
我要你和这个…
电影大亨谈谈 把强尼的事摆平
若没有其他事 我想去参加我女儿的婚礼了
If there's nothing else, I'd like to go to my daughter's wedding.
Carlo, we're going to take the picture.
卡洛，我们要拍照了
Wait a minute.
等一下
不，麦克，我不行
No, Michael. Not me.
Okay, that's it. Just like that. Hold it!
好了，就是这样，别动！
- You need a little more heat on that arc. - Start talking.
好了，开始说吧！
我是强尼方亭的朋友派来的
I was sent by a friend of Johnny Fontane.
他的朋友是我的委托人
This friend would give his friendship to Mr Woltz,
若是华尔斯先生能帮他个小忙
他将会感激不尽
if Mr Woltz would grant us a favour.
Woltz is listening.
继续说下去
Give Johnny the part in that war film you're starting next week.
把你下周开拍的 新片男主角让强尼担任
And what favour would your friend grant Mr Woltz?
他的朋友会回报我什么好处？
He could make your future union problems disappear.
你若有工会问题 我的委托人能摆平
And one of your stars has just moved from marijuana to heroin.
而你旗下一位抽大麻的大牌
现在吸起海洛因了
你想要威胁我吗？
Are you trying to muscle me? Listen, you son-of-a-bitch!
绝对没有，我只是…
听着 你这个油腔滑调的王八蛋
Let me lay it on the line. Johnny Fontane will never get that movie!
让我对你及你的老板说清楚 不管他是何许人
强尼方亭绝对得不到那个角色
No matter how many Dago Guinea greaseballs come out of the woodwork!
我不在乎有多少意大利的 移民来找我麻烦
我是德裔爱尔兰人
- I'm German-Irish. - Listen here, my Kraut-Mick friend.
坦白告诉你，德国朋友
- I'm going to make trouble for you! - I'm a lawyer. I haven't threatened...
你大祸临头了 你甚至不会晓得是谁扁你
华尔斯先生，我是位律师 我不是来威胁你
I know New York's big lawyers. Who are you?
我认识纽约的每位大律师 你是谁？
I have a special practice. I handle one client. I'll wait for your call.
我的执业情况特别 只为一位委托人办事
你有我的电话号码 我等你电话
告诉你，我很喜欢你的电影
By the way, I admire your pictures very much.
Check him out.
摸清他的底细
- It's really beautiful. - Look at this.
真是美极了
看看这个 原本是用来装饰王宫的
- It used to decorate a king's palace. - Very nice.
很漂亮
Why didn't you say you work for Corleone?
你为何不说 你为柯里昂阁下做事
我以为你只是个市井流氓
I thought you were some cheap hustler Johnny was running in.
是强尼派来勒索我的
除非真的必要 否则我不想提起他的名字
- I only use his name when necessary. - How's your drink?
-你的酒还好吗？ -很好
- Fine. - Now I'll show you something beautiful.
到这边来 让你看看真正漂亮的东西
You do appreciate beauty, don't you?
你的眼光应该不错吧？
There you are. 600,000 dollars on four hoofs.
这里！这匹马价值六十万元
我敢说俄国沙皇 也从未在马身上花那么大笔钱
I bet Russian czars never paid that for a single horse.
Khartoum.
达通！
I'm not going to race him, though. I'm going to put him out to stud.
不过我不会用它们来比赛 我要它们当种马
Thanks, Tony.
-谢谢，汤尼！ -不必客气！
我们去吃点东西吧！
Let's get something to eat.
Corleone is Johnny's godfather.
柯里昂是强尼的教父
To the Italian people that's a very sacred, close relationship.
对意大利人而言 那是种宗教上神圣的亲密关系
I respect it. Tell him to ask me anything else. This favour I can't give him.
我很敬重这点
告诉他除了这件事
我什么都答应
He never asks a second favour when he's been refused the first.
他被拒绝一次后 不会再要求第二次
You don't understand. Johnny Fontane never gets that movie.
你不了解 强尼方亭永远别想演那部电影
That part is perfect for him. It'll make him a big star.
他很适合那个角色
会让他成为巨星
但我要让他走投无路
I'm going to run him out of the business, and let me tell you why.
我告诉你为什么
Johnny Fontane ruined one of Woltz International's most valuable proteges.
强尼毁了一位华尔斯国际公司 最有前途的女星
We trained her for five years. Singing, acting, dancing lessons.
五年来我们不断地训练她
歌唱课、表演课、跳舞课
我在她身上投资了无数的金钱
I spent hundreds of thousands of dollars on her, to make her a big star.
我要让她成为一位巨星
Let me be even more frank.
让我更坦白的告诉你
让你知道我不是铁石心肠 也不是势利眼
To show you that I'm not a hard-hearted man. That it's not all dollars and cents.
She was beautiful. She was young and innocent!
她年轻漂亮，天真无邪
She's the greatest piece of ass I've had and I've had them all over the world.
我拥有她就等于拥有全世界
Then Johnny Fontane comes along with his olive oil voice and Guinea charm.
然后强尼方亭出现了
带着磁性的嗓音 加上意大利的魅力
And she runs off.
把她拐走了
她跑掉了使我非常难堪
She threw it all away just to make me look ridiculous!
而我这种地位的人 无法忍受难堪
And a man in my position can't afford to be made to look ridiculous!
你马上给我滚
You get the hell out of here!
If that goombah tries any rough stuff, tell him I'm no bandleader.
若是那混球想对我动粗
你告诉他我不是乐队领班
Yeah, I heard that story.
我听过那个故事了
Thank you for dinner and a very pleasant evening.
谢谢你的晚餐款待
Maybe your car can take me to the airport.
也许你能派车送我去机场
Mr Corleone insists on hearing bad news immediately.
柯里昂先生坚持 坏消息要立刻回报
- You're not too tired, are you, Tom? - No, I slept on the plane.
-你不会太累吧？汤姆 -我在飞机上睡过了
I have the Sollozzo notes here.
我这里有索拉索的资料
Now...
众人皆知，索拉索是土耳其人
Sollozzo is known as The Turk. He's supposed to be very good with a knife,
他应该善于用刀
but only in matters of business with reasonable complaint.
但只有发生利益冲突时 才会使用
His business is narcotics.
他是做毒品生意的
He has fields in Turkey, where they grow poppy.
他们在土耳其种罂粟
In Sicily he has plants to process them into heroin.
在西西里有工厂提练成海洛因
He needs cash, he needs protection from the police.
他需要现金
以及在毒品交易时 需要警方的保护
He'll give a piece of the action. I don't know how much.
我无法查出保护费价钱多少
在纽约是塔塔基利亚家族 在保护他
The Tattaglia family is behind him here. They have to be in it for something.
他们一定也想分占利益
山尼柯里昂
- What about his prison record? - One term in Italy, one here.
-他的犯罪前科呢？ -一次在意大利，一次在这
He's known as a top narcotics man.
他是众所周知的大毒枭
- Santino, what do you think? - A lot of money in that white powder.
山提诺，你认为呢？
白粉可以赚大钱
Tom?
我赞成，毒品比什么都好赚
Yes. There's more money in narcotics than anything else.
就算我们不加入，别人也会
If we don't get into it, somebody else will, maybe the five families.
也许是五大家族之一 也许全部都会
With that money they can buy more police and political power.
他们会用毒品赚到的钱 买通警方和政客
Then they come after us.
到时就会赶上我们
Now we have unions and gambling, and that's great, but narcotics is the future.
现在我们掌握了工会及赌场
而他们却掌握未来最好的东西 毒品
If we don't get a piece of that action, we risk everything in ten years' time.
我们若不能分一杯羹
我们可能会失去一切
我不是指现在而是在十年之内
So? What's your answer going to be, Pop?
你的答案是什么呢？爸爸
Don Corleone.
柯里昂阁下
我需要有势力的友人
I need a man who has powerful friends.
我需要一百万元的现金
I need a million dollars in cash.
我需要你手中掌握的政客
I need those politicians that you carry in your pocket, like nickels and dimes.
- What is the interest for my family? - 30 per cent.
-对我家族有什么利益？ -三成
In the first year your end should be three, four million dollars.
第一年你就可进帐三四百万元
然后还会增加
And then it would go up.
And what is the interest for the Tattaglia family?
塔塔基利亚家族 会得到什么好处？
My compliments.
我的敬意
I'll take care of them, out of my share.
我会从我那一份当中分给他们
So I receive 30 per cent for finance,
我提供财务、政治 和法律的保护，可以分到三成
political influence and legal protection?
没错
That's right.
Why do you come to me? Why do I deserve this generosity?
你为何来找我
我为何值得你这么慷慨？
若你能考虑投资一百万元现金
If you consider a million dollars in cash just finance,
我就会向你敬礼，柯里昂阁下
ti saluto, Don Corleone.
I said that I would see you, because I heard you were a serious man,
我肯见你是因为 我听说你是个正直的人
to be treated with respect.
所以我以礼相待
But, I must say no to you.
但是我必须拒绝你
And I'll give you my reason.
我会告诉你原因
It's true, I have a lot of friends in politics.
没错，我是有很多政界的朋友
但若他们知道我在搞毒品生意 而不再是赌博时
They wouldn't be friendly long if I was involved in drugs instead of gambling,
他们就不再是我的朋友
which they regard as a harmless vice, but drugs is a dirty business.
他们认为赌博 只是些无伤大雅的事业
但毒品是败坏德性的生意
-但是柯里昂阁下… -对我而言一个人以何为生
It doesn't make any difference to me what a man does for a living.
并没有什么差别
But your business is... a little dangerous.
但你这种生意…有一点危险性
若你还是担心安全的问题
If you're worried about security, the Tattaglias will guarantee it.
塔塔基利亚会做保证的
- The Tattaglias would guarantee our... - Wait a minute.
你是说塔塔基利亚家族 会保证我们的投资…
等一下
你看我把孩子都给宠坏了
I have a sentimental weakness for my children, and I spoil them.
他们说话非常没有分寸
They talk when they should listen. But anyway...
但总之，索拉索先生
Signor Sollozzo, my no is final. I wish to congratulate you on your new business.
我的决定还是不行
我要恭喜你的生意
我知道你会很成功… 我祝你好运
I know you'll do well, and good luck.
尤其是你的生意 不会与我的冲突
Especially since your interests don't conflict with mine. Thank you.
谢谢
Santino.
山提诺
Come here.
到这来
你是怎么回事？
What's the matter with you? Your brain is going soft from playing with that girl.
我看你和女孩子胡搞之后 脑子退化了
Never tell anybody outside the family what you're thinking again.
别让外人知道你在想什么
走吧
Go on.
汤姆，这是什么乱七八糟的？
Tom, what's this nonsense?
那是强尼送的 他主演了那部新电影
It's from Johnny. He's starring in that new film.
好了，把它拿走
- Take it away. - Take it over there.
把它放到那去
And...
还有
...tell Luca Brasi to come in.
叫路卡布拉西到这来
I'm a little worried about this Sollozzo fellow.
我对这索拉索有点担心
Find out what he's got under his fingernails.
我要你弄清楚他在耍什么把戏
到塔塔基利亚那边去
Go to the Tattaglias.
让他们以为你 与我们家族不融洽
Make them think that you're not too happy with our family
尽量查
and find out what you can.
I got something for your mother and for Sonny
我买了东西给令堂
还有给弗雷多的领带 给汤姆的钢笔
and a tie for Freddy, and Tom Hagen got the Reynolds pen.
-你圣诞节想要什么？ -我只要你
- What do you want for Christmas? - Just you.
Andiamo, Fredo.
醒醒，弗雷多
叫保利备车，我们要走了
- Tell Paulie to get the car. - Okay, Pop.
好的，爸
我来开车，保利今早生病了
I'll have to get it myself. Paulie called in sick this morning.
Paulie's a good kid. I don't mind getting the car.
保利是个好孩子 我不介意自己开车
谢谢
Buon Natale, caro. Grazie.
-路卡，我是布诺塔塔基利亚 -我知道
- Luca! I'm Bruno Tattaglia. - I know.
想喝杯威士忌吗？
先暖和一下
我不喝酒
You know who I am?
你知道我是谁吗？
I know you.
我认识你
你和塔塔基利亚家族谈过了 对吧？
You have been talking to the Tattaglia family... right?
I think you and I can do business.
我认为我们可以一起做些生意
I need someone strong like you.
我需要像你这么壮的人
I heard you are not happy...
我听说你与柯里昂家族不和
...with the Corleone family.
Want to join me?
想加入我们吗？
What's in it for me?
我能得到什么好处？
$50,000 to start with.
起薪五万元
Not bad!
还不坏
同意了？
Agreed?
Tom! Tom Hagen. Merry Christmas.
汤姆哈金，圣诞快乐
我很高兴遇见你
- Glad to see you. I want to talk to you. - I haven't got time.
-我想跟你聊聊 -我没时间
Make time, Consigliere. Get in the car.
为我们拨点时间，军师，上车
你担心什么？
What are you worried about? If I wanted to kill you, you'd be dead already.
我想杀你的话你早已死了
上车
Get in.
- Fredo, I'm going to buy some fruit. - Okay, Pop.
稍候一下，弗雷多 我买点水果
好的，爸
Merry Christmas. I want some fruit.
圣诞快乐，我要买些水果
那个给我
弗雷多
爸爸
Would you like me better if I were a nun? Like in the story.
麦克，我若是修女 你是否会更喜欢我
就像小说中的角色 你知道吗？
No.
不会
若我是英格丽褒曼 你是否会更喜欢我？
- What if I were Ingrid Bergman? - Now, that's a thought.
这个想法不错
Michael.
麦克
No, I wouldn't like you better if you were Ingrid Bergman. What's the matter?
不，你若是英格丽褒曼 我不会更喜欢你的
-麦克 -怎么回事？
（维多柯里昂被谋杀）
They don't say if he's dead or alive.
上面没说他是死是活
- Sonny, it's Michael. - Where have you been?
-山尼！我是麦克 -麦克，你到哪去了？
-他没事吧？ -我们还不知道
- Is he all right? - We don't know yet.
There are all kinds of stories. He was hit bad, Mikey.
他伤的很重，麦克
- Are you there? - Yeah, I'm here.
-你还在吗？ -是的，我在这
-你到哪去了？我很担心 -汤姆没说我打过电话吗？
- Where have you been? I was worried. - Didn't Tom tell you I called?
No. Look, come home, kid. You should be with Mama, you hear?
听我说，回家来 你应该在这陪妈妈的
好的
Oh, my God.
我的天啊
Sonny!
山尼
Stay back there.
- Who is it? - Open up, it's Clemenza.
-谁？ -开门！我是克里曼沙
又有你老头的消息了
There's more news about your old man.
Word is out that he's already dead.
街头谣传他已经死了
-你是怎么回事？ -山尼，别激动
- What's the matter with you? - Take it easy!
保利在哪？
- Where was Paulie? - Sick. He's been sick all winter.
保利病了，他整个冬天都病了
- How often? - Only three, four times.
-他病了几次？ -病了三四次
-弗雷多并不想另找保镖 -马上接他来
- Freddy didn't want a new bodyguard. - Pick him up now.
我不管他病的有多重
I don't care how sick he is. Bring him to my father's house right now.
只要他还在呼吸 我要你把他带到家父的房子去
现在！明白吗？现在！
- You want anyone sent over here? - No. Go ahead.
好，你要我派人到这边来吗？
不用！去吧！
我会派几个人到家里来
I'm going to have a couple of our people come over to the house.
-你好 -山尼柯里昂吗？
- Hello? - Santino Corleone?
- Yeah. - We have Tom Hagen.
-我就是 -汤姆哈金在我们手上
In three hours he'll be released with our proposition.
约三小时后我们会释放他
Listen to what he has to say before you do anything.
在你做任何事之前 先听听他说的话
What's done is done. Don't lose that famous temper of yours, Sonny.
木已成舟
先别发怒，好吗？山尼
I'll wait.
不会的，我会等
Your boss is dead.
你的老板死了
I know you're not in the muscle end of the family, so don't be scared.
我知道你在家族中 是不喜欢动武
所以我不想要你感到害怕
I want you to help the Corleones and me.
我要你帮助柯里昂还有帮我
We got him outside his office about an hour after we picked you up.
接了你约一小时后
我们已在他办公室外干掉他了
Drink it.
喝吧
It's up to you to make peace between me and Sonny.
现在全看你的了
让我与山尼和平解决一切
Sonny was hot for my deal, wasn't he?
山尼对我的主意很热中 不是吗？
而且你知道那么做是对的
And you knew it was the right thing to do.
- Sonny will come after you. - That will be his first reaction, sure.
山尼会不惜一切的来追杀你
那会是他的第一个反应
So you have to talk sense into him. The Tattaglia family is behind me.
所以要你去劝劝他
塔塔基利亚家族全力支持我
纽约其他的家族 也会不惜一切防止全面的战争
The other New York families will go along with anything to prevent war.
Let's face it, with all due respect, the Don - rest in peace - was slipping.
让我们面对现实吧！汤姆
我们全都尊敬他
但教父已今非昔比 愿他安息！
Ten years ago, could I have gotten to him?
十年前我能对付他吗？
Well, now he's dead, Tom, and nothing can bring him back.
但现在他已经死了
他死了，汤姆
没什么能让他复生
You've got to talk to Sonny, to the Caporegimes, Tessio, fat Clemenza.
所以你得和山尼谈谈
也得说服两个大头目 泰西欧及肥克里曼沙
It's good business, Tom.
那是笔好生意，汤姆
I'll try. But even Sonny won't be able to call off Luca Brasi.
我试试看
但即使是山尼也阻止不了路卡
Yeah, well...
这个…路卡让我来担心
Let me worry about Luca.
You just talk to Sonny.
你只管说服山尼
And the other two kids.
及他另外两个兄弟
-我尽力而为 -很好
- I'll do my best. - Good.
Now you can go.
现在…你可以走了
我不喜欢暴力，汤姆 我是个生意人
I don't like violence, Tom. I'm a businessman.
流血代价太高了
Blood is a big expense.
He's still alive.
他还活着
They hit him with five shots, and he's still alive!
他们打了他五枪，他还活着
That's bad luck for me, and bad luck for you if you don't make that deal.
那对我是件坏事
若你不能谈成那档事 对你也不是好事
令堂在医院陪令尊
Your mother is at the hospital with your father. Looks like he'll pull through.
看起来他能度过难关 谢天谢地
It's a lot of bad blood. Sollozzo, Philip Tattaglia, Bruno Tattaglia, Ramon...
-全是塔塔基利亚家族策划的 -你认为如何？
教父认为这是设计好的
- You gonna kill all those guys? - Stay out of it.
-你要把那些人全杀掉？ -别插手这件事，麦克
索拉索是关键 除掉他一切就好办了
If you get rid of Sollozzo, everything falls into line.
What about Luca? Sollozzo thinks he can control him.
路卡呢？ 索拉索认为他可以控制路卡
我不知道
If Luca sold out, we're in a lot of trouble.
如果路卡出卖我们 我们就有大麻烦了
- Has anyone been in touch with Luca? - We've been trying all night.
有人能与路卡连络上吗？
我试了一整夜但没有人接
- Hey, do me a favour... - Luca never sleeps over with a broad.
麦克，帮我个忙 打电话给路卡
他从不在外留宿 他每次办完事会立刻回家
Well, Tom, you're consigliere. What do we do if the old man dies?
汤姆，你是军师
若是老头死了 我们该怎么办？
If we lose the old man, we lose the political contacts and half our strength.
我们万一失去了老头
我们就会失去政界的连系
The other New York families might support Sollozzo to avoid a long war.
纽约其他的家族 为了避免长期的战争
可能会联合支持索拉索
This is almost 1946. Nobody wants bloodshed anymore.
现在是1946年了
没有人想再流血了
If your father dies...
若是令尊死了
...you make the deal.
就由你做决定了，山尼
- Easy to say. He's not your father. - I'm as much a son as you or Mike.
你说来容易，那不是你父亲
我与你跟麦克 对他来说都是儿子
What is it?
什么事？
- Paulie, I told you to stay put. - The guy at the gates has a package.
保利，我叫你在外面守着
大门的人说收到一包东西
泰西欧，去看看是什么
Tessio, go see what it is.
你要我留在这？
- Shall I stay? - Yeah. Are you all right?
是的，留在这，你还好吧？
是的，我很好
- I'm fine. - There's food. Are you hungry?
有点吃的，你饿了吗？
- No. - A drink? Brandy will sweat it out.
不，没关系的
喝杯酒吧！ 一点白兰地能让你舒服点
-好吧 -去吧！孩子
- Go ahead. - That might be a good idea.
那或许是个好主意
Take care of that son-of-a-bitch. Paulie sold out the old man.
我要你立刻处置那个王八蛋
保利出卖了老头，那个混蛋
- Make that the first thing on your list. - Understood.
我不想再见到他
这是你第一件先要解决的工作
-明白吗？ -明白
Mickey, tomorrow, get some guys and go to Luca's apartment.
麦克，明天你带几个人…
到路卡的公寓去看看 等他出现
也许我们不该让麦克 太直接涉入
Maybe we shouldn't get Mike mixed up in this too directly.
听我说…待在家里接电话 那会有大帮助的
Hanging around the house on the phone would be a big help.
再试着打给路卡
Try Luca again.
- What's this? - A Sicilian message.
-这是什么？ -那是西西里人的口信
It means Luca Brasi sleeps with the fishes.
那表示路卡布拉西与鱼同眠了
- I'm going. - When will you be home?
-我现在要走了 -你今晚几点会回家？
Probably late.
我不知道，也许会很晚
- Don't forget the cannoli! - Yeah, yeah, yeah.
-别忘了油饼 -知道了
Rocco, sit on the other side. You block the rear-view mirror.
罗可，坐到另一边去
你挡住后照镜了
开始大发雷霆了
Sonny's running wild. He wants to go to mattresses already.
他想要跟对手开战了
我们得在西区找个地方藏匿
We have to find a spot on the West Side. Try 309 West 43rd Street.
你试试西43街309号
- Know a good spot on the West Side? - I'll think about it.
-你知道西区有何好地方吗？ -我想想看
Think while you're driving. I want to hit New York this month.
你开车的时候想想好吗？
我这个月要找一天到纽约去
Watch the kids.
倒车出去时留意小孩子
Paulie, go down 39th Street, pick up 18 mattresses and bring me the bill.
保利，我要你到39街去
去买18个垫子
然后把帐单拿给我
Yeah, all right.
确定要干净的
Make sure they're clean, because the guys will be there a long time.
因为我们要在那待段长时间
它们是干净的，他们说消毒过
- They're clean and exterminated. - That's a bad word to use.
消毒，用那个字很不好
消毒，听听这个砘
Exterminate! Watch out, so we don't exterminate you!
小心点，我们才不会为你消毒
那真是好笑
停到路旁去好吗？我要小便
Pull over. I've got to take a leak.
把枪留下
Leave the gun. Take the cannoli.
把油饼给我
麦克…
Hey, Mike! Hey, Mikey!
- Yeah. - Phone call!
你的电话！
- Who is it? - Some girl.
-是谁？ -女孩子
- Hello. Kay? - How's your father?
-你好，凯 -令尊还好吗？
他很好，他能活过来
He's going to make it.
I love you.
我爱你
I love you!
- Michael? - Yeah, I know.
-麦克 -是，我知道
- Tell me you love me. - I can't talk.
告诉我你爱我
我不能说
Can't you say it?
你不能说吗？
I'll see you tonight.
我们今晚见
Why don't you tell that nice girl you love her?
麦克，你为何不说你爱她
I love you with all my heart. If I don't see you again soon, I'm going to die!
我全心全意的爱你
我若不快点见到你，我会死的
到这来，孩子，学点东西
Come and learn something. You might have to cook for 20 guys some day.
有一天 你也许得为20个男人煮饭
You start with a little oil, then fry some garlic.
一开始先倒点油，炸大蒜
然后放番茄，炒一下
Throw in some tomatoes, tomato paste, fry it and make sure it doesn't stick.
别让它粘锅底
煮开了之后，加入香肠及肉丸
You get it to a boil, you shove in all your sausage and meatballs.
Add a little bit of wine.
再加一点点酒
And a little bit of sugar. That's my trick.
以及…
一点点糖
那是我的秘方
Cut the crap. I have more important things for you. How's Paulie?
你别说废话了
我有更重要的事要让你去做
保利呢？
You won't see him no more.
保利，你再也见不到他了
你要去哪？
- Where are you going? - To the city.
到城里去
派保镖跟他一起去
- Send bodyguards with him. - I'm going to the hospital...
我只是去医院看爸爸
我不管，派人跟他一起去
He'll be all right. Sollozzo knows he's a civilian.
他不会有事的 索拉索知道他是“平民”
-小心点 -是的
- Be careful. - Yes, sir.
Send somebody with him anyway.
还是派人跟他一起去
- I have to go. - Can I go with you?
-我得走了 -我能与你一起去吗？
不，凯，那里有刑警还有记者
No, Kay. There will be detectives there, people from the press.
我在车上等你
I'll wait in the cab.
I don't want you to get involved.
我不要你卷入这件事
When will I see you again?
我何时能再见到你？
Go back to New Hampshire, and I'll call you at your parents' house.
回新罕布夏去
我打电话去你父母家找你
- When will I see you again, Michael? - I don't know.
我何时才能再见到你？麦克
我不知道
你在这里干什么？
What are you doing here? You're not supposed to be here.
现在不是探病时间
我是麦克柯里昂
I'm Michael Corleone. This is my father.
这是家父
What happened to the guards?
这里没人，守卫到哪去了？
Your father had too many visitors. They interfered with hospital service.
令尊访客太多 妨碍了医院的作业
警察在十分钟前要他们离去了
The police made them leave about ten minutes ago.
Get me Long Beach 45620, please.
请帮我接长滩45620
Nurse. Wait a minute. Stay here.
护士，等一下，先别走
Sonny, I'm at the hospital. I got here late, there's nobody here.
山尼，我是麦克，我在医院
听着，我很晚才到这儿 这没有人
No Tessio's men, no detectives, nobody. Papa's all alone.
泰西欧的人不在 也没有刑警，没有人
爸爸单独一个人在这
- Don't panic. - I won't panic.
-别惊慌 -我不会惊慌
I'm sorry, but you will have to leave.
我很抱歉，但你必须离去
We're going to move him to another room. Can you disconnect the tubes?
你帮我把家父移去另一间房
现在你是否能把这个拆开
我来推病床
- That's out of the question! - Do you know my father?
-那是不可能的 -你认识家父吗？
他们会来杀了他，懂吗？
Men are coming here to kill him. Do you understand?
Help me, please.
现在请你帮我忙
- Who are you? - I am Enzo, the baker.
-你是谁？ -我是安索，那个糕饼师
- Remember me? - Enzo.
-你还记得我吧？ -安索
是的，我是安索
You'd better go, there's going to be trouble.
你最好离开这，安索 这里会有麻烦
If there is trouble, I'll stay here to help you. For your father.
若是有麻烦，我留在这帮你
为了令尊！…
好吧！听我说
Listen. Wait for me outside, in front of the hospital, all right?
在医院大门外面等我，好吗？
我马上出来，快去！
I'll be out in a minute.
好的…
Just lie here, Pop. I'll take care of you now.
好好休息吧！爸！
我会照料你的
我和你在一起
I'm with you now.
I'm with you.
把这个丢掉
Get rid of these. Come here.
到这来
Put your hand in your pocket, like you have a gun. You'll be all right.
把手放在口袋里 就像你有把枪
你不会有事的
You did good.
你做的很好
这是干什么？
I thought all you Guinea hoods were locked up!
我以为把你们这些混混 全关住了
你在这里干什么？
守家父的人是怎么回事？
- Why isn't anyone guarding my father? - You little punk!
你这个小混蛋，竟敢管我的事
Don't you tell me my business! I pulled them off.
是我把那些人全赶走的
- Stay away from this hospital! - Not until my father's room is guarded.
你马上离开这医院
除非你派人守护家父 否则我不会走
- Phil, take him in! - The kid's clean, Captain.
菲尔，把他带回去
那孩子是清白的，队长
- He's a war hero. He's never been... - I said take him in!
他是个服役荣归的英雄 从未和黑手党混在一起
该死的，我说把他带回去
- What's The Turk paying you? - Take a hold of him. Stand him up.
索拉索付你多少钱 来陷害家父？
把他抓牢，让他站稳
Stand him up straight.
I'm the Corleone's attorney. These men are hired to protect Vito Corleone.
我是柯里昂家的律师
这些人是私家侦探
雇来保护维多柯里昂的
他们有携带武器的执照
They're licensed to carry firearms.
若是你干预，我们明早法庭见
If you interfere, you'll have to appear before the judge and show cause.
Let him go.
好了，让他走
走吧
这些新面孔是怎么回事？
- What's with all the new faces? - We'll need them now.
我们现在需要他们
After the hospital thing, Sonny got mad.
经过医院的事之后 山尼气疯了
We hit Bruno Tattaglia this morning.
我们今晨四点 干掉了布诺塔塔基利亚
Jesus Christ.
老天爷
Looks like a fortress around here.
这里看起来像是座城堡
Tommasuccio! Hey... 100 buttonmen on the street 24 hours a day.
街上一天24小时 都有一百个枪手在巡逻
那土耳其人敢露出一根汗毛 就挂了
That Turk shows one hair on his ass, he's dead.
Mike, let me look at you.
麦克，到这里来，让我看看你
You're beautiful, beautiful. You're gorgeous.
你漂亮极了，漂亮极了
The Turk wants to talk! Imagine the nerve of the son-of-a-bitch.
你们听我说
那土耳其人想谈判
那王八蛋紧张了
昨晚整我们，今天想和谈
- He wants a meeting today. - What did he say?
-他怎么说？ -他怎么说？
What did he say... He wants us to send Michael to hear the proposition.
他要我们派麦克去
并保证那条件 好到我们不会拒绝
He promises that the deal is too good to refuse.
- And Bruno Tattaglia? - That's part of the deal.
那布诺塔塔基利亚呢？
那是条件的一部分
他作为对家父挨枪的补偿
- He cancels out what they did to Father. - We should listen to them.
山尼，我们该听听他们怎么说
不！…不再听了，军师
No more! Not this time, Consigliere.
No more meetings, discussions, or Sollozzo tricks.
不再和谈、不再讨论 不再上索拉索的当
I want Sollozzo, or we go to war...
你去跟他们说，我要索拉索
否则我们就开战！
- The other families... - They hand me Sollozzo!
山尼，其他家族不会支持的
叫他们把索拉索交给我
山尼，令尊不会喜欢的 这是生意，不能感情用事
This is business, not personal!
- They shot my father... - Even that was business, not personal.
那我父亲就该挨枪了？
即使是令尊挨枪也是生意
不是个人的事，山尼
Then business will have to suffer. Do me a favour.
那生意必须要停，行吗？
听着，帮我个忙，汤姆
别再建议我如何让事情过去
No more advice on how to patch things up. Just help me win.
只要帮我赢，好吗？
I found out about Captain McCluskey, who broke Mike's jaw.
我查出了打断麦克下巴 那麦克劳斯基队长的事
他怎么样？
He's definitely on Sollozzo's payroll, and for big money.
他肯定在索拉索的规费名单中 而且是很大一笔钱
麦克劳斯基是索拉索的保镖
McCluskey has agreed to be The Turk's bodyguard.
你必须要了解，山尼
当索拉索跟警察队长勾搭上时
So when Sollozzo is being guarded, he's invulnerable.
没人可以碰他了
过去从没人胆敢干掉纽约警官
Nobody has ever gunned down a New York police captain.
All the families would come after you. The Corleone family would be outcasts!
那会是个大灾难
所有五大家族都会追杀你 山尼
柯里昂家族会被孤立！
Even the old man's political protection would run for cover.
即使是老头的 政治保护都会消失
Do me a favour. Take this into consideration.
拜托你
别轻举妄动
All right, we'll wait.
好吧！我们等
We can't wait. We can't wait.
我们不能等
No matter what Sollozzo says, he's going to kill Pop.
不管索拉索答应什么 他会杀了爸爸的
那是他的关键
That's the key for him. We've got to get Sollozzo.
必须干掉索拉索
- Mike is right. - Let me ask you something.
麦克说的对
那个谈判就没有必要了
这个麦克劳斯基呢？
What about this McCluskey? What do we do with this cop?
我们要拿这个条子怎么办？
They want to have a meeting with me, right?
他们想与我开会，对吧？
It will be me, McCluskey and Sollozzo.
那会是我 麦克劳斯基及索拉索
Let's set the meeting.
我们来安排会议
Get our informers to find out where it's going to be held.
我们查清楚会议地点在哪里
We insist it's a public place. A bar, a restaurant.
必须是公开场所，酒吧或餐厅
Some place where there are people, so I feel safe.
人多的地方对我比较安全
They'll search me when I meet them, right?
我与他们一见面 他们会搜身，对吧
So I can't have a weapon on me.
那么我身上不能有武器
若克里曼沙能想出一个办法
But if Clemenza can figure out a way to have a weapon planted there for me...
能预先把武器放在那
...then I'll kill them both.
那我就能杀了他们两个
你要怎么做？乖乖的大学生
Nice college boy. Didn't want to get mixed up in the family business.
你不是不想和家族中的事 混在一块吗？
现在因为他打了你 你就想干掉他？
Now you want to shoot a police captain because he slapped you?
This isn't like the army! You have to get close and get their brains on your suit.
你以为这里是什么？军队吗？
在一哩以外开枪打他们？
你必须离这么近，砰一声
他们的脑浆会溅到你身上
-山尼… -你太感情用事了
You're taking this very personal.
Tom, this is business and he's taking it personal.
汤姆，这是公事 而他却感情用事
- Where does it say you can't kill a cop? - Mikey...
谁说不能杀条子的？
-别这样，麦克 -汤姆，慢着
I'm talking about a cop who's mixed up in drugs, a dishonest cop.
他是个跟毒品买卖有关的条子
他是个不诚实的条子
A cop who got mixed up in the rackets and got what was coming.
和毒贩混在一起 终于得到报应
That's a terrific story. We have newspaper people on the payroll, right?
那是个好极了的故事
报社不是有我们的人吗？
- They might like a story like that. - They might.
他们也许对那故事有兴趣
他们也许，只是也许
It's not personal, Sonny. It's strictly business.
不是感情用事，山尼 纯粹是公事
It's as cold as they come. Impossible to trace, so you don't worry about prints.
做过表面处理了，追踪不到的
不用担心指纹
我在扳机和手把上 贴了特殊胶布
I put a special tape on the trigger and the butt. Try it.
来，试试看
Is the trigger too tight?
怎么了？扳机太紧了？
我的耳朵好辛苦
My ears!
我没安装消声器 那样才能吓走旁观的人
I left it noisy, so it scares away any pain-in-the-ass innocent bystanders.
You've shot them both. Now what do you do?
好了，你杀了他们两个
接下来你怎么办？
- Sit down, finish my dinner. - Don't fool around.
坐下吃完我的晚餐
别开玩笑
Let your hand drop to your side and let the gun slip out.
就让你的手垂下，让枪滑掉
每个人都认为你还拿着枪
Everybody will still think you've got it. They'll stare at your face,
他们会瞪着你的脸，麦克
so walk out fast, but don't run.
所以快步离开那地方但不要跑
Don't look anybody in the eye, but don't look away either.
别直视任何人 但也不要看其他地方
他们会怕的不敢瞪你 相信我，不必担心
They'll be scared stiff, so don't worry about nothing.
You'll be all right. You'll take a vacation, nobody knows where,
你若可以全身而退
可以休个长假到哪里都可以
and we'll catch the hell.
而我们会处理善后
-你认为后果会有多糟？ -他妈的蛮糟的
- How bad do you think it will be? - Pretty goddamn bad.
All the other families will probably line up against us.
可能所有的家族 会联合对付我们
那没关系的
These things have to happen every five, ten years. Gets rid of the bad blood.
每五年或十年都会发生一次
害群之马必须要除掉
Been ten years since the last one. You have to stop them at the beginning.
上一次到现在已有十年了
要先发制人
Like they should have stopped Hitler in Munich, not letting him get away with it.
就像要在慕尼黑 制止希特勒一样
他们容忍了希特勒 麻烦就大了
You know, Mike, we were all proud of you. Being a hero and all.
知道吗？麦克
我们都以你为荣 你是个英雄
Your father too.
你父亲也是
Nothing. Not a hint. Absolutely nothing.
没有任何线索，什么都没有
Even Sollozzo's people don't know where the meeting will be held.
索拉索的人也不知在哪里开会
How much time do we have?
我有多少时间？
They're going to pick you up outside Jack Dempsey's in an hour and a half.
一小时半以后 他们在达西路口接你上车
- We could put a tail on them. - Sollozzo would lose our ass.
我们派个人追踪他们
索拉索会在街上乱转 甩掉我们的人
- What about the negotiator? - He's playing pinochle with my men.
来找我们谈判的人呢？
他在那边和我的手下玩纸牌
- He's happy. They're letting him win. - Too risky. Maybe we should call it off.
他很高兴，我们在让他赢
对麦克太危险了
山尼，也许我们该取消
要麦克平安回来
The negotiator plays cards until Mike is back safe.
我们才会让那个人走的
- He could blast whoever is in the car. - They'll expect that.
何不干脆干掉车上的人呢？
太危险了，他们会注意的
Sollozzo might not even be in the car, Sonny!
索拉索也许根本就不在车上
I'll get it.
我来接
Louis' restaurant in the Bronx.
布朗区的路易士餐厅
可靠吗？
- Is it reliable? - My man in McCluskey's precinct.
麦克劳斯基的分局里有我的人
A police captain is on call 24 hours a day. He'll be there between 8 and 10.
队长必须24小时待命
他八点到十点会去那里
- Anybody know this joint? - Sure, I do. It's perfect for us.
有谁知道那个地方
我知道
对我们太理想了
A small family place, good food. Everyone minds his business. Perfect.
家庭餐厅，食物精美
各吃各的，太理想了
彼得，那儿有个旧式马桶
They've got an old-fashioned toilet. You know, the box and the chain thing.
你知道就是水箱有吊链的那种
We might be able to tape the gun behind it.
我们或许可把枪用胶带绑在那
好的，麦克，你去餐厅
All right. Mike, you go to the restaurant,
you eat, talk for a while, you relax. Make them relax.
你一面吃一面聊，别紧张
也可以使对方轻松下来
然后你站起来去上厕所
Then you go to take a leak. No, better still, you ask permission to go.
你得先徵求对方同意再去
回来时就开枪
Then you come back blasting. Two shots in the head apiece.
别失误，对准头颅各开两枪
听着，我要一个好手去藏枪
I want somebody very good to plant that gun.
I don't want him coming out with just his dick.
我不希望我弟弟出来时
手无寸铁
- The gun will be there. - You drive him and pick him up.
枪会在那的
你开车送他，事后再接他回来
Let's move.
来吧！我们动身了
Did he tell you to drop the gun right away?
他告诉过你事成之后 立刻丢枪吗？
Yeah, a million times.
几百万次了
切记！朝每人头部开两枪 一出厕所后就打
Don't forget. Two shots apiece in the head as soon as you come out.
How long do you think it will be before I can come back?
你们认为要多久我才能回家？
At least a year.
至少得一年，麦克
我会转告妈 你临走前不能去看她
I'll square it with Mom, that you're not seeing her before you leave and...
I'll get a message to that girlfriend when the time is right.
我会告诉你女朋友的
Take care.
保重！
Take care, Mike.
保重！麦克
I'm glad you came. I hope we can straighten everything out.
我很高兴你来了，麦克
希望我们能把事情谈妥
这种事太可怕了 我并不希望发生这种事
It's not the way I wanted things to go. It should never have happened.
不该发生这种事的
I want to straighten everything out. I don't want my father bothered again.
我会在今晚解决一切
我不希望我爸烦心
I swear on my children that he won't be, Mike.
会解决的，麦克
我以我孩子之名发誓
But you have to keep an open mind when we talk.
不过谈的时候，你得坦诚才行
希望你不像令兄的坏脾气
I hope you're not a hothead like Sonny. You can't talk business with him.
简直没办法和他谈正事
（意大利文）
He's a good kid.
他是个好孩子
I'm sorry about the other night, Mike.
那晚的事我很抱歉，麦克
I've got to frisk you, so turn around. On your knees, facing me.
我得搜你的身，转过来
跪在椅子上，脸向我
我想我干这行已经嫌老了
I guess I'm getting too old for my job. Too grouchy.
太多话了
Can't stand the aggravation. You know how it is.
受不了别人的激怒 你该明白吧
He's clean.
他没带砘
Going to Jersey?
到新泽西去？
Maybe.
也许
Nice work, Lou.
漂亮极了，路
（路易士餐厅）
- How's the food in this restaurant? - Try the veal. It's the best in the city.
这里的意大利菜 味道还可以吧？
很棒
试试这里的小牛肉 是本市最棒的
I'll have it.
给我来一份
快！
好了
我要和麦克用意大利文交谈
- I'm going to speak Italian to Mikey. - Go ahead.
请便
（意大利文）
What I want...
对我而言最重要的是
What's most important to me...
...is that I have a guarantee. No more attempts on my father's life.
保证家父的性命安全
What guarantees can I give you? I'm the hunted one!
你要我怎么保证？麦克
我也是惊弓之鸟
I missed my chance. You think too much of me, kid.
我也失手
你太看重我了，孩子
我没有那么精明
I'm not that clever.
All I want is a truce.
我想要的只是息战而已
我必须要上厕所，可以吗？
I have to go to the bathroom. Is it all right?
When you got to go, you got to go.
想去就去吧
He's clean.
我搜过了，他没带砘
别去太久
Don't take too long.
I've frisked a thousand punks.
我搜过好几千人了
（意大利文）
（警方追捕警察杀手）
（本市黑道瓦解）
（警察队长与毒贩勾结）
（黑社会头子巴西尼 接受警方盘问）
（黑社会大火拼）
（黑社会大亨 维多柯里昂返家）
好了，转进来
好了，你接手
Okay, you take over.
我爱你，爷爷
I love you, Grandpa.
I'm sorry, Pa. He doesn't know you yet.
对不起，爸，他还不认识你
- Hey, big guy. Give it to Grandpa. - Okay.
小砘铮念给爷爷听！
好，我祝你早日康复，爷爷 我希望能快点见到你
"I hope you get well, Grandpa, and wish I see you soon. Your grandson Frank."
爱你的孙子，法兰克
多乖巧
走吧！到外面去
Go with your mother.
把他们带到楼下去吧！
Take them downstairs.
妈！
Go on, Carlo, you too.
走吧！卡洛，你也是
Go on.
走吧
你要烤鸡吗？那是他最喜欢的
我知道，但他能吃多少呢？
- What's the matter with you, Carlo? - Shut up and set the table.
你怎么了？卡洛
闭嘴，去摆桌子吧！
Since McCluskey's killing, the police have cracked down on our operations.
自从麦克劳斯基被杀后
警方瓦解了我们多数业务
And also the other families. There's been a lot of bad blood.
其他的家族也是一样
牺牲很多
They hit us, so we hit them back.
他们攻击我们
我们反击
Through our newspaper contacts we've been able to put out material
透过我们报社中的连系 我们提供了不少内幕
很多麦克劳斯基 跟毒贩索拉索勾结的事
about McCluskey's link with Sollozzo in the drug rackets.
所以风声已经没有那么紧了
So things are loosening up.
And I sent Fredo to Las Vegas, under the protection of Don Francesco of L.A.
还有我派弗雷多去拉斯维加斯
在洛杉矶的法兰西斯科阁下 会给予他保护
- I want him to rest. - I'm going to learn the casino business.
-我要他休息一会儿 -我要去学赌场的事
Where's Michael?
麦克在哪？
It was Michael who killed Sollozzo.
杀索拉索的是麦克
But he's safe. We're starting to work to bring him back.
不过他很安全，别担心
我们会把他弄回来的
你查出塔塔基利亚 躲在哪儿没？
Did you find out where that old pimp Tattaglia is hiding? I want him now.
我要他的命！现在！
-听我说，山尼 -什么事？
Sonny, things are starting to loosen up.
现在局势才刚刚缓和下来
If you go after Tattaglia, all hell will break loose. Pop can negotiate.
你若去追塔塔基利亚
又会引起一场大战的
等事情平静一点 让爸爸去协调
不，爸爸在身体好转之前 什么都不能做
- He must get better first. I'll decide... - War is costly. We can't do business.
我要决定什么对我们最有利
好的，可是你那场火拼 使我们损失很多
没有任何进帐，我们不能做事
他们也不行，别担心
- Neither can they. Don't worry about it! - We can't afford a stalemate.
-他们没有我们损失那么大 -请你别担心这点
- No more stalemate. I'll kill the bastard! - You're getting a great reputation!
我会以宰了那老混蛋来做结束
是，你现在名声很大 你一定很得意吧！
Do as I say! If I had a Sicilian wartime consigliere, I wouldn't be in this shape!
依照我叫你做的去做
该死的，我若有个西西里人 来当我的战略军师
我就不会落到这种地步了
爸爸有杰安可 看看我有什么？
Pop had Genco. Look what I got.
I'm sorry. I didn't mean that.
对不起，我不是有意的
Ma made a little dinner. It's Sunday.
妈妈煮了晚餐，今天是星期天
Niggers are having a good time with our policy banks in Harlem.
黑人对我们哈林区的 银行新政策非常满意
Driving new Cadillacs, paying 50 per cent on a bet.
开着新凯迪拉克 我先帮他们付一半的钱
That's because they've started making big money.
从他们开始赚钱时 我就知道这会发生
爸爸从来不在餐桌上 当着孩子们谈他的公事
Poppa never talked business at the table.
-闭嘴，康妮… -不准你叫她闭嘴，知道吗？
- Shut up, Connie... - Don't you ever tell her to shut up.
别干预
Don't interfere.
I'd like to talk to you after dinner. I could do more for the family...
山尼、汤姆 吃过饭后，我想与你们谈谈
-我对家族也许能帮很多的… -我们不在餐桌上讨论公事
We don't discuss business at the table.
我向你致敬，汤马西诺阁下
I kiss your hand, Don Tommasino.
麦克
Why are you so far from the house?
你为何离房子那么远？
You know I'm responsible to your father for your life.
你可知万一你出了事 我要向令尊负责的
The bodyguards are here.
保镖们都在这
It's still dangerous...
还是十分危险
我听纽约的山提诺说的
We've heard from Santino in New York...
Your enemies know you're here.
你的敌人知道你在这了
Did Santino say when I can go back?
山提诺有没有说 我何时能回去？
Not yet.
还不行
It's out of the question.
目前是不可能的
谢谢
Where are you going now?
你现在要去哪里？
柯里昂村
Take my car.
坐我的车去
我想走路
I want to walk.
小心点
Be careful.
麦克，柯里昂村到了
Where have all the men gone?
所有的男人都到哪去了？
They're all dead from vendettas.
他们全都在战争中死了
这里是死者的姓名
There are the names of the dead.
Hey, hey, take me to the America, G.I.!
Hey, hey, take me to the America, G.I.! Clark Gable!
America! Take me to the America, G.I.! Clark Gable, Rita Hayworth!
Mamma mia what a beauty.
我的老天！好一个美女
I think you got hit by the thunderbolt.
你好像中邪了一样
In Sicily women are more dangerous than shotguns.
麦克
在西西里，女人比猎枪还危险
Did you have a good hunt?
打猎有收获吗？
You know all the girls around here?
你认识这一带所有的女孩吗？
We saw some real beauties.
One of them struck our friend like a thunderbolt.
我们看到几位真正的美人
She would tempt the devil himself.
其中一位让我们的朋友触电了
她可真够骚了
她全身上下都很美
Really put together.
Such hair, such mouth!
那么漂亮的头发、嘴
The girls around here are beautiful... but virtuous.
这一带的女孩都很美 而且很贞洁
This one had a purple dress...
这个穿着紫色衣服
And a purple ribbon in her hair.
头发上绑着紫色的缎带
A type more Greek than Italian.
看起来像希腊人而非意大利人
Do you know her?
你认识她吗？
不认识
There's no girl like that in this town.
在本镇没有那样子的女孩
My God, I understand!
我的天！我明白了
有什么不对了？
What's wrong?
Let's go.
我们走
It's his daughter.
是他女儿
叫他出来
Tell him to come here.
Call him.
Fabrizio, you translate.
法布利奇欧，你翻译
是的，先生
I apologise if I offended you.
我若冒犯了你，我道歉
I'm a stranger in this country.
我初到贵地
我无意冒犯你和令媛
I meant no disrespect to you or your daughter.
I'm an American, hiding in Sicily.
我是个美国人 到西西里来避风头
My name is Michael Corleone.
我的名字是麦克柯里昂
There are people who'd pay a lot of money for that information.
有人会为了钱 而出卖我在此的消息
But then your daughter would lose a father...
但那样令媛会失去父亲
...instead of gaining a husband.
而不是得到一位丈夫
我想认识你女儿
I want to meet your daughter.
但要在你的同意下
With your permission, and under the supervision of your family.
及在你的家人的监督之下
With all respect.
我绝对是诚心诚意
星期天早上到我家来 我叫维提
Come to my house Sunday morning. My name is Vitelli.
谢谢
What's her name?
她叫什么名字？
艾波洛妮亚
很美的名字
这是小女艾波洛妮亚
这位是麦克柯里昂先生
谢谢
等我回来干你
I'll knock you dizzy.
废话少说
Save it for the library.
We've got to pick up my sister.
来吧！我们得去接我妹妹
What's the matter?
怎么了？
- It was my fault! - Where is he?
-是我的错 -他在哪？
山尼，拜托，是我的错
It was my fault. I hit him.
山尼，是我的错 是我先开始打他的！
I started a fight with him. I hit him, so he hit me...
求你，山尼，我先打他的
-我… -好了
I'm just going to get a doctor to take a look at you.
我只是叫医生来看你，好吗？
Sonny, please don't do anything.
山尼，求你别动手
What's the matter with you? What am I going to do?
好，你是怎么了？ 我会怎么做？
Make that baby an orphan before he's born?
我会让你肚里的孩子 做遗腹子吗？
好了吗？
You spic slobs still betting Yankees?
这些砘锇蜒蠡队打得惨兮兮
叫他们不要再接受投注了
Tell them to stop taking in action.
We lost enough money last week.
我们上周末输的钱够多了
卡洛，到这来…
Come here, come here!
If you touch my sister again, I'll kill you.
你再碰我妹妹一下 我会杀了你
（意大利文）
Hey! We weren't expecting you, Kay. You should call.
没想到你会来，凯 怎么不先打个电话来
Yes, I have. I've tried writing and calling.
我有打，我写过信也打过电话
我要和麦克连络
- I want to reach Michael. - Nobody knows where he is.
没有人知道他在哪
我们知道他没事但如此而已
All we know is that he's all right.
- What was that? - An accident, but nobody was hurt.
-怎么了？ -那是件车祸但没有人受伤
Tom, will you give this letter to Michael. Please?
汤姆
请你把这封信交给麦克 好吗？
If I accepted that, a court could prove I have knowledge of his whereabouts.
我若接受了 法院可以证实我晓得他在哪里
你有耐心点，凯 他会与你连络的，好吗？
He'll get in touch with you.
I let my cab go, so can I call another one, please?
我让我的计程车走了 我是否能进去打电话叫一辆？
来吧！对不起，来吧！
Come on. Sorry.
- Hello? - Is Carlo there?
卡洛在吗？
- Who is this? - A friend of Carlo.
-你是哪位？ -我是卡洛的朋友
Tell him that I can't make it tonight until later.
你告诉他我今晚没空
Bitch!
贱人
- Dinner's on the table. - I'm not hungry.
-晚餐在桌上了 -我还不饿
- The food is getting cold. - I'll eat out later.
-晚餐在桌上快凉了 -我有约了
You just told me to make you dinner!
你刚叫我给你做晚餐的
-滚开好吗？ -你才滚开
She has a filthy mouth, this Guinea brat.
你这个意大利婊子
好，全都打破了！
That's it, break it all, you spoiled Guinea brat. Break it all!
你这被宠坏的女娃！ 全打破了！
你为何不把那个妓女 带回家吃晚饭？
Why don't you bring your whore home for dinner?
也许我会，有何不可？
Maybe I will.
现在把它清干净！
- Clean it up! - Like hell I will!
我不要！我才不要！
You skinny, spoiled brat. Clean it up! Clean it up!
清干净！贱人
清干净！我说清干净！
Clean it up! I said, clean it up! Clean it up!
清干净！
Clean it up. Clean that up, you...
不！
清干净！他妈的
清干净！…
Clean it!
Clean it up! Yeah, kill me. Be a murderer, like your father!
清干净！
来！杀我！ 像你爸一样当凶手！
- All you Corleones are murderers! - I hate you!
来吧！ 你们姓柯里昂的全是凶手
Come on, kill me!
来吧！贱人
来吧！杀我！滚！
Get out of here!
-我恨你！ -快点！否则我要杀你了
- I hate you! - Now I'll kill you.
你这意大利贱货
You Guinea brat. Get out of here!
滚出来
不！
康妮，怎么回事？
Connie, what's the matter? I can't hear you.
我听不见你说的，什么事？
Connie, talk louder. The baby's crying.
康妮，说大声点，孩子在哭
Santino, I can't understand. I don't know.
山提诺，我听不懂，我不明白
Yeah, Connie.
什么事？康妮？
You wait there.
听我说，你在那等着
No, you just wait there.
不，你在那等着就对了
王八蛋！
Son-of-a-bitch.
- Son-of-a-bitch! - What's the matter?
-怎么回事？ -王八蛋！
Open the goddamn gate! Get off your ass.
快开门，站起来
Sonny!
山尼
-山尼 -滚开
- Sonny. - Get out of here!
跟他一起去，快点
Go after him, go on!
Son-of-a-bitch. Come on!
王八蛋，快点…
把那个给我
Give me a drop.
My wife is crying upstairs.
我太太在楼上哭
I hear cars coming to the house.
我听见车子到家里来
Consigliere of mine,
我的好军师
tell your Don what everyone seems to know.
所有人都知道 只有我毫不知情
I didn't tell Mama anything.
我没告诉妈任何事
I was about to come up and wake you and tell you.
我正预备去叫醒你，并告诉你
But you needed a drink first.
但你需要先喝杯酒
Yeah.
Well, now you've had your drink.
现在你喝过酒了
They shot Sonny on the causeway. He's dead.
他们在收费站杀了山尼
他死了
I want no inquiries made.
我不要追查此事
I want no acts of vengeance.
我不要复仇
I want you to arrange a meeting...
我要你安排一次会议
与五大家族的族长
...with the heads of the five families.
This war stops now.
这场火拼该终止了
打电话给包纳萨拉
Call Bonasera.
I need him now.
我现在需要他了
This is Tom Hagen. I'm calling for Vito Corleone, at his request.
我是汤姆哈金
维多柯里昂要我打这个电话
You owe your Don a service.
你欠教父一次人情
He has no doubt that you will repay it.
他相信你会回报他的
他在一小时后 会到你的殡仪馆去
He will be at your funeral parlour in one hour. Be there to greet him.
请在那等待
Well, my friend, are you ready to do me this service?
我的朋友
你预备为我服务了吗？
Yes. What do you want me to do?
是的，但你要我怎么做？
我要你尽你一切的力量和技巧 好好为他化妆
I want you to use all your powers and all your skills.
我不要他母亲看到他这个样子
I don't want his mother to see him this way.
Look how they massacred my boy.
看看他们是怎么对我的孩子？
It's safer to teach you English!
-教你英文会安全一点 -我会英文，星期一
I know English...
Monday, Tuesday, Thursday, Wednesday, Friday, Sunday, Saturday.
星期二、星期四、星期三
-星期五、星期日、星期六 -好极了！
Greetings, Don Tommasino.
How are things in Palermo?
你好，汤马西诺阁下
Michael is teaching me to drive... watch, I'll show you.
麦克在教我开车
我开给你看
How are things in Palermo?
家里的一切都还好吧？
Young people don't respect anything any more...
年轻人不再尊重任何事了
times are changing for the worse.
时代越变越糟
这地方对你已变得太危险了
This place has become too dangerous for you.
I want you to move to a villa near Siracusa... right now.
我要你搬到西拉古莎 附近的别墅
What's wrong?
有什么不对了？
Bad news from America.
由美国传来的坏消息
你哥哥山尼，他们杀了他！
Your brother, Santino, they killed him.
我们走了！你答应的
Let's go... you promised.
Get the car.
-法布利奇欧！ -什么事？
备车
你要自己开吗？老板
Are you driving yourself, Boss? Is your wife coming with you?
是的
你太太跟你一起去吗？
No, take her to her father's house until things are safe.
不，我要你送她回娘家 等一切安全点再说
Okay, anything you say.
好的，随你吩咐，老板
Calo, where is Apollonia?
卡罗，艾波洛妮亚呢？
She's going to surprise you. She wants to drive.
她想给你个惊喜，她要开车
She'll make a good American wife.
她会当个好的美国太太
等一下，我去拿行李
Wait, I'll get the baggage.
Fabrizio!
法布利奇欧
Where are you going?
你要去哪？
Wait there! I'll drive to you.
麦克，在那等，我开过去
No, Apollonia!
不！艾波洛妮亚…
巴西尼阁下
Don Barzini, I want to thank you for helping me organise this meeting,
谢谢你帮我安排这次会议
and the other heads of the five families from New York and New Jersey.
还有纽约和新泽西 其他五大家族的族长
Carmine Cuneo from the Bronx,
布朗区的卡麦克里安诺
and from Brooklyn...
以及…布鲁克林的
...Philip Tattaglia.
菲立浦塔塔基利亚
And from Staten Island
由史坦登岛来的
维多史特基
we have with us Victor Strachi.
And the other associates that came as far as from California and Kansas City
及由加州堪萨斯来的同道
以及全国其他各地区 所来的朋友
and all the other territories of the country. Thank you.
谢谢你们
How did things ever get so far?
事情怎么会演变成如此？
I don't know.
我不晓得
It was so unfortunate, so unnecessary.
是那么的不幸及那么的没必要
Tattaglia lost a son, and I lost a son.
塔塔基利亚失去了一个儿子
我也是
我们该停手了
We're quits. And if Tattaglia agrees,
若是塔塔基利亚同意
then I'm willing to let things go on as before.
我愿意让事情恢复以前的局面
We're grateful to Don Corleone for calling this meeting.
我们都很感谢柯里昂阁下 召开这次会议
We all know him as a man of his word. A modest man who listens to reason.
我们都了解他是个有信用的人
他为人谦虚，总是能讲道理
Yes, Don Barzini. He's too modest.
是的，巴西尼阁下
他太谦虚了
He had all the judges and politicians in his pocket.
所有的法官与政客 没有不听他指示的
He refused to share them.
他却拒绝与我们分享
我何时拒绝过与大家分享？
When did I ever refuse an accommodation?
在座的全都认识我
All of you know me.
When did I ever refuse, except one time? And why?
除了一次以外 我何时拒绝过？
你们知道为什么
因为我相信毒品生意 在往后几年会毁了我们
Because I believe this drug business will destroy us in the years to come.
It's not like gambling or liquor or even women,
这不像赌、酒和女人
which is something that most people want, but is forbidden by the Church.
这些是人们想要的东西 只是教会不准我们做而已
即使警察过去在赌博等方面 愿意协助我们
Even the police that have helped us in the past with gambling and other things
are going to refuse to help us when it comes to narcotics.
但一提到毒品 他们会拒绝帮忙
I believed that then... and I believe that now.
我以前那么想 现在想法依然不变
Times have changed.
时代变了
It's not like the old days, when we could do anything we wanted.
不像昔日了
我们能做任何我们想做的事
A refusal is not the act of a friend.
你拒绝合作实在不够朋友
柯里昂阁下握有全纽约 法律界以及政客的势力
If Don Corleone had all the judges and politicians, then he must share them
他就必须与大家分享
or let others use them. He must let us draw the water from the well.
让大家都能利用他们
他必须让我们分汲利益 大家一起发财
Certainly he can present a bill for such services.
当然他能因这种服务 而向大家收费
After all, we're not communists.
毕竟我们不是共产党
I also don't believe in drugs.
我同样的也不相信毒品
For years I paid my people extra, so they wouldn't do that kind of business.
多年来我付手下优厚的待遇
使他们不去沾毒品
Somebody says to them "I have powders."
避免有人来找他们 并且说我有白粉
你只要投资三千元到四千元
"If you put up 3-4,000 dollar investment, we can make 50,000 distributing."
就可以赚到五万元
They can't resist. I want to control it as a business, keep it respectable.
他们怎能抗拒得了
我想以正派的方法 来经营毒品生意
I don't want it near schools, I don't want it sold to children.
我不要它们接近学校
我不要把它们卖给孩子
That's an infamia.
那是残害幼苗
In my city we would keep the traffic to the coloured.
我只想卖给那些黑人 或是在有色人种中流通
They're animals, so let them lose their souls.
他们反正是动物 所以让他们去坠落吧
I hoped that we could come here and reason together.
我本希望能合理的讨论一些事
And I'm willing to do whatever is necessary to find a peaceful solution.
身为一个讲道理的人
我愿意为此事 找个和平解决之道
We are agreed. The traffic in drugs will be permitted, but controlled.
那么我们全都达成协议
毒品生意可以做但要有限制
Don Corleone will give us protection in the east, and there will be peace.
柯里昂阁下会给我们 东部的保护
然后我们和平相处
I must have strict assurance from Corleone.
但我必须有柯里昂阁下的 确切保证
As time goes by and his position becomes stronger,
万一他的地位越来越坚固之后
他是否会采取复仇行动
will he attempt any individual vendetta?
We are all reasonable men. We don't have to give assurances.
听着我们这全是讲理的人
我们不需像是律师般 给什么确切保证
你谈到复仇
You talk about vengeance.
Will vengeance bring your son back to you?
复仇会让你的儿子复活吗？
Or my boy to me?
或者我的儿子？
I forgo the vengeance of my son.
我不会再去计较我儿子的死
但我有个自私的要求
But I have selfish reasons.
My youngest son was forced to leave this country...
我的小儿子被迫离开这个国家
...because of this Sollozzo business.
全都因为这索拉索的事
我必须安排让他安全的回来
And I have to make arrangements to bring him back here safely.
Cleared of all these false charges.
洗脱种种无中生有的罪名
But I'm a superstitious man.
而我是个迷信的人
If an unlucky accident should befall him, if he should be shot by a police officer,
若是他不幸发生意外
或被警察开枪打死
or if he should hang himself in his jail cell,
或在牢里上吊
or if he's struck by a bolt of lightning,
或是他被闪电击中
then I'm going to blame some of the people in this room.
那我会怪罪于 在这房间内的诸位
And that I do not forgive.
到那时候我就不会再客气了
But, that aside...
但除了那个以外
...let me say that I swear...
我以我孙子的性命发誓
...on the souls of my grandchildren,
that I will not be the one to break the peace we've made here today.
我不会是打破 我们今天和议的人
Should I insist that all of Tattaglia's drug middlemen have clean records?
当我见塔塔基利亚的人时
应否坚持那些毒品中间人 都没有前科？
Mention it. Don't insist.
提出来无妨，不要坚持
- Barzini will know without being told. - You mean Tattaglia.
巴西尼这种人你不说他也明白
你是说塔塔基利亚
Tattaglia's a pimp. He could never have outfought Santino.
塔塔基利亚是个下三滥？
他根本没本事干掉山提诺
But I didn't know until this day that it was Barzini all along.
我在今天以前并不晓得
一直是巴西尼在主使
Come on, Nancy.
来吧！南西
Keep together, everyone. Brian.
大家紧跟在一起，布莱恩
Okay, all right.
好的…
How long have you been back?
你回来多久了？
I've been back a year.
一年了
Longer than that, I think.
也许还不只
It's good to see you, Kay.
见到你真好，凯
I'm working for my father now, Kay.
我现在为我父亲做事
He's been sick. Very sick.
他病了，病的很重
But you're not like him. You told me you weren't going to become like your father.
但是你不像他，麦克
我以为你不会成为 令尊那样的人
那是你所告诉我的
My father is no different than any other powerful man.
家父与其他有权的人一样
Any man who's responsible for other people.
就是那种要对其他人 负责任的人
Like a senator or president.
像是参议员或是总统
你知道你说这些话有多天真
- How naive you sound. - Why?
为什么？
They don't have men killed.
参议员及总统不杀人
Who's being naive, Kay?
是谁天真？凯
My father's way of doing things is over. Even he knows that.
家父做事的那一套已过时了
连他都晓得那一点
In five years the Corleone family is going to be completely legitimate.
我是说在五年之内
柯里昂家族会完全合法化
相信我！
Trust me. That's all I can tell you about my business. Kay...
我很清楚我未来的走向
凯
Michael, why did you come here? Why?
麦克，你为何到这来？
为什么？
What do you want with me after all this time? I've been calling and writing.
你究竟想要我怎么样？
这么多年来 你不打电话也不写信
I came because I need you. I care for you.
我来这是因为我需要你 我关心你
别再说了，麦克
- Please stop it, Michael. - Because... I want you to marry me.
因为…
我要你嫁给我
- It's too late. - Please, Kay...
太迟了…
凯！…
I'll do anything you ask to make up for what's happened to us.
我会做任何事 以弥补过去所发生的事
Because that's important, Kay. Because what's important is that...
因为那很重要！凯
重要的是因为…
...we have each other. That we have a life together.
我们拥有彼此
而且我们要共度一生
That we have children. Our children.
我们会有孩子
我们的孩子
Kay, I need you.
凯
我需要你
而且我爱你
And I love you.
Barzini's people chisel my territory and we do nothing about it!
巴西尼的人抢我们的地盘
而我们却无能为力
- Soon I'll have no place to hang my hat! - Be patient.
再过不久布鲁克林 我连落脚的地方都没有了
有耐性点
I'm not asking for help. Just take off the handcuffs.
我不是求你帮忙 只是不想受制肘
- Be patient. - We must protect ourselves.
再忍耐点
我们必须保护自己
给我个机会再培养一些新人
- Let me recruit some new men. - No.
不！
- Barzini would get an excuse to fight. - Mike, you're wrong.
-我不要给巴西尼藉口来开战 -麦克，你错了
Don Corleone...
柯里昂阁下
You once said that one day Tessio and me could form our own family.
你曾说过要让我 与泰西欧自立门户
Till today I would never think of it. I must ask your permission.
今天以前我想都不敢想
但现在我要求你的批准
Michael is now head of the family.
现在由麦克当家 如果他答应我就祝福你
If he gives his permission, then you have my blessing.
After we make the move to Nevada
等我们搬到内华达州后
you can leave the Corleone family and go on your own.
你就可由柯里昂家族分出 自立门户
但得在我们搬到内华达州之后
- How long will that be? - Six months.
那得花多少时间？
六个月
Forgive me, but with you gone, me and Pete will come under Barzini's thumb.
原谅我，教父
但当你走了后
我与彼得迟早 会成为巴西尼的靶
I hate that Barzini. In six months' time there will be nothing left to build on.
我恨那该死的巴西尼
六个月之后 我们已经搞不出什么玩意了
- Do you have faith in my judgement? - Yes.
你对我的判断有信心吗？
是的
- Do I have your loyalty? - Always, Godfather.
你仍对我忠心吗？
是的，忠心不二，教父
Then be a friend to Michael. Do as he says.
那么就当麦克的朋友吧
照他所说的去做
Things are negotiated that'll solve your problems and answer your questions.
现在有些事仍在磋商
你们的问题和困难 全都可以得到解决
That's all I can tell you now.
目前我只能这么说
Carlo, you grew up in Nevada.
卡洛，你在内华达长大的
When we make our move there, you'll be my right-hand man.
当我们搬的时候 你会是我的左右手
Tom Hagen is no longer consigliere. He'll be our lawyer in Vegas.
汤姆哈金不再做军师了
他将会担任 我们在拉斯维加斯的律师
That's no reflection on Tom, just how I want it.
我对汤姆没有不满 但我不要他再当军师
况且有我父亲在 他可以做我最佳的军师
If I ever need help, who's a better consigliere than my father? That's it.
就是这样了
- Thank you, Poppa. - I'm happy for you, Carlo.
-谢谢，爸爸 -我为你高兴，卡洛
Mike... Why am I out?
麦克，我为何出局了？
你不适合当乱局中的军师
You're not a wartime consigliere, Tom.
Things may get rough with the move.
我们一搬到内华达后 事情会变得更棘手
Tom.
汤姆
I advised Michael. I never thought you were a bad consigliere.
我向麦克建议过
我从未认为你不适合当军师
I thought Santino was a bad Don, rest in peace.
我认为山提诺不适合当家
愿他安息
我信任麦克和你一样
Michael has all my confidence, just as you do.
But there are reasons why you must have no part in what is going to happen.
但是…
不让你参与往后的行动 是有理由的
- Maybe I could help. - You're out, Tom.
我多少能帮得上忙
用不着了，汤姆
I can't get over the way your face looks. So good!
我实在无法不去注意你的脸
它的确看起来很棒
This doctor did some job. Did Kay talk you into it? Hey, hey, hey!
这位医生的工夫确实不错
是凯说服你去的吗？
慢着！把它们留下这
Leave them out here. He's tired and wants to clean up.
我们待会再处理它们
他累了，他想梳洗一下
好了，让我来开门，好吗？
Let me open the door, all right?
- Hello, Mike! Welcome to Las Vegas! - All for you, kid! It's all his idea.
麦克！欢迎光临拉斯维加斯！
你认为如何？
全是他的主意，对吧？
你的哥哥弗雷多
- Your brother Freddy. - Girls?
是你弄来的女孩子，不是吗？
I'll be right back. Keep them occupied.
我马上回来，你先招呼一下
- Anything you want, kid, anything. - Who are the girls?
-你要什么全都有 -那些女孩子是谁？
- That's for you to find out. - Get rid of them, Fredo.
这得要你自己去弄清楚了
把她们弄走，弗雷多
麦克
- Hey, Mike... - I'm here on business. Get rid of them.
弗雷多，我是来这公干
我明天就走，现在把她们弄走
I'm tired. Get rid of the band too.
我累了，把乐队也弄走
Hey, take off. Take off. Let's go.
走吧！…走就对了
Hey, that's it. Hey, Angelo.
快点！安琪拉，快走
走吧！闪了！
Hey, come on! Scram!
走吧，亲爱的，走了
Come on, honey. I don't know what's the matter with him, Johnny.
我不知道，强尼
我不知道他是怎么回事 对不起
没关系，弗雷多
Sorry.
走吧！亲爱的 我不知道，他大概累了
I don't know. He's tired.
What happened to Moe Greene?
莫格林呢？
He had some business. He said to give him a call when the party started.
他说他有别的事
他说派对开始时，给他个电话
Well, give him a call.
那就打电话给他
强尼，你好吗？
- Johnny, how are you? - Nice to see you, Mike.
麦克，再看到你真高兴
我们全都以你为傲
- We're proud of you. - Thanks.
谢谢，麦克
Sit down, I want to talk to you. The Don is proud too.
坐，强尼，我要跟你谈谈
教父也以你为傲，强尼
Well, I owe it all to him.
我的一切都归功于他
He knows how grateful you are. That's why he'd like to ask a favour of you.
他知道你会感恩
所以他想请你帮个忙
麦克，我能做些什么？
Mike, what can I do?
We're thinking of giving up our interests in the olive oil business and settle here.
柯里昂家族想放弃 橄榄油的生意
而在这里安顿下来
Moe will sell us his share of the casino and the hotel, so we'll own all of it. Tom!
莫格林会把他旅馆 及赌场的股份卖给我们
使得家族能拥有全部的生意
汤姆！
Are you sure? Moe loves the business. He never said nothing about selling.
麦克，这点你确定吗？
莫格林很爱这门生意
从未对我提过要卖掉它的事
I'll make him an offer he can't refuse.
我会提个他无法拒绝的条件
See, Johnny...
知道吗？强尼…
We figure that entertainment would draw gamblers to the casino.
我们认为表演一定可以 吸引赌客到赌场来
We hope you'll sign a contract to appear five times a year.
我们希望你签个合约 一年来此登台五次
Perhaps convince some of your friends in the movies to do the same.
也许…
顺便找些你电影圈中的朋友
We're counting on you.
我指望你了
Sure, Mike. I'll do anything for my godfather.
当然，麦克
为了教父我什么都肯做 你晓得的
Good.
很好
Hey, Mike! Hello, fellows. Everybody's here. Freddy, Tom.
麦克，各位好，大家都在这
弗雷多，汤姆…
- Good to see you. - How are you, Moe?
-见到你真好，麦克 -你好吗？莫
你点的都到齐了吗？
Have everything? Specially prepared food, the best dancers, and good credit.
大厨会为你煮最好吃的菜 还有最棒的舞群
给房间里的每个人 都弄点筹码来
Draw chips for everybody, so they can play on the house.
好让他们到场子里去玩玩
我的信用好的 够买下你的股份吗？
Is my credit good enough to buy you out?
买我的股份？
Buy me out?
The casino, the hotel. The Corleone family wants to buy you out.
赌场，这家旅馆
柯里昂家族想买下 你全部的生意
柯里昂家族想买下 我全部的生意？
The Corleone family wants to buy me out? No, I buy you out.
不，我买下你们的 你不能买下我的
Your casino loses money. We can do better.
你的赌场在赔钱
也许我们能经营的好一点
- You think I'm skimming off the top? - You're unlucky.
你认为我在走下坡了？麦克
你运气不好
你他妈的别让我笑了
You Guineas make me laugh.
I took Freddy in when you had a bad time, and now you try to push me out!
在你们有难时
我帮你们的忙 给弗雷多一份差事
现在你想把我弄出去
慢着
你让弗雷多来这
You did that because we bankrolled your casino
是因为柯里昂家族 支援你的赌场
and the Molinari family guaranteed his safety. Let's talk business.
因为海岸的莫伦纳家族
保证他的安全
现在我们在谈生意 别岔开话题
Yes. First of all, you're all done. You don't have that kind of muscle anymore.
好，我们来谈生意，麦克
首先，你们都完蛋了
柯里昂家族已经衰退了
教父生病了，对吧？
The Godfather is sick. You're getting chased out of New York by the others.
你们被巴西尼及其他家族 赶出了纽约
你以为这里是什么？
Do you think you can come to my hotel and take over?
你以为能到我的 地盘上来接管？
I talked to Barzini. I can make a deal with him and still keep my hotel!
我和巴西尼谈过了
我有办法和他打交道
也不至于失去旅馆
Is that why you slapped my brother around in public?
所以你当众支使我哥哥？
That was nothing, Mike. Moe didn't mean nothing by that.
不，麦克，那不算什么
莫也不是那个意思
当然他偶尔说话很大声但是…
He flies off the handle sometimes, but we're good friends.
莫和我是好朋友，对吧？莫
I have a business to run. I've got to kick asses sometimes.
我是在做事业！
当然要催紧点，事情才会顺利
我是偶尔和弗雷多意见不合
We had an argument, so I had to straighten him out.
只不过是为了“训练”他一下
你“训练”我哥哥？
You straightened my brother out?
He was banging cocktail waitresses! Players couldn't get a drink.
他跟酒廊的女侍鬼混
客人喝酒没人送
What's wrong with you?
你是怎么回事？
I leave for New York tomorrow. Think about a price.
我明天回纽约
你考虑一个价钱吧
Son-of-a-bitch!
I'm Moe Greene! I made my bones when you were out with cheerleaders.
你知道我是谁吗？我是莫格林
我发迹时你还在玩泥巴
Wait a minute, Moe. I have an idea.
等一等，莫，我有个主意
Tom, you're the consigliere. Talk to the Don...
汤姆！汤姆，你是军师
你可以和教父谈，解释给他听
Just a minute. Don is semi-retired and Mike is in charge of the family business.
慢着！教父已经半退休了
家族现在由麦克管事
If you have anything to say, say it to Michael.
你有话就向麦克说吧
麦克，你不能到拉斯维加斯来
Mike, you don't come to Las Vegas and talk to a man like Moe Greene like that!
和莫格林那种人那样说话
Fredo...
弗雷多
You're my older brother, and I love you.
你是我哥，我爱你
但不准你再联合外人 起来反对自己家族
But don't ever take sides with anyone against the family again.
绝对不准
I have to see my father and his people, so have dinner without me.
我必须先去看我父亲 和他的手下
你们先吃饭吧
麦克
This weekend we'll go out. We'll go to the city, see a show and have dinner.
这个周末我们可以出外游玩
到城里看电影吃饭，我保证
Your sister wants to ask you something.
麦克
麦克，你姐姐有事想问你
- Let her ask. - She's afraid to.
-她可以问我！ -她怕你
They want you to be godfather to their boy.
康妮和卡洛 要你当他们孩子的教父
-到时再说吧！ -你会吗？
- We'll see. - Will you?
Let me think about it. Come on.
让我考虑一下 到时再说，来吧
巴西尼想要先对付你
Barzini will move against you first.
He'll set up a meeting with someone you absolutely trust.
他会找个你信任的人 来安排见面
Guaranteeing your safety.
并保证你的安全
And at that meeting you'll be assassinated.
但你一出席会议，他就杀了你
I like to drink wine more than I used to.
我现在比以前爱喝酒了
- Anyway, I'm drinking more. - It's good for you, Pop.
而且越爱喝就喝的越多
对你有好处的，爸爸
I don't know.
我不知道
Are you happy with your wife and children?
你太太和小孩过的还快乐吧？
- Very happy. - That's good.
非常快乐
很好
I hope you don't mind the way I keep going over this Barzini business.
希望你不介意 我一直在谈巴西尼
- No, not at all. - It's an old habit.
不，一点也不
这是我的老习惯
I spend my life trying not to be careless.
我花了一辈子 就学会了“小心”
Women and children can be careless, but not men.
女人和小孩能够粗心大意 但男人不行
- How's your boy? - He's good.
-你儿子还好吗？ -很好
He looks more like you every day.
你知道他越来越像你了
He's smarter than I am. He's three and can read the funny papers.
他比我聪明
才三岁就懂得看漫画了
Read the funny papers.
看漫画
I want you to arrange for a telephone man to check all in- and out-going calls.
我要你安排一个电话公司的人
查每一个进出这里的电话
- I did it already. I took care of that, Pop. - That's right. I forgot.
-我已经做了，爸 -任何一个人都有可能
-爸！我已经处理那件事了 -没错，我忘了
What's the matter?
怎么回事？
What's bothering you?
是什么困扰着你？
I'll handle it. I told you I can handle it, so I'll handle it.
我应付得了，我说能，我就能
I knew that Santino would have to go through all this.
我知道山提诺 势必会染指家族事业
And Fredo...
还有弗雷多
Fredo was, well...
弗雷多他…
But I never wanted this for you.
但我从来没…
我从来没想到要你参与
我干了一辈子，没什么遗憾的
I worked my whole life. I don't apologise for taking care of my family.
我照顾了我的家人
And I refused to be a fool,
但是我绝不当傻瓜
dancing on a string held by all those big shots.
让那些大人物在幕后操纵我
我不必道歉，那是我的命运 但是我想过…
I don't apologise. That's my life, but I thought that...
...that when it was your time, you would be the one to hold the strings.
有一天你能当那些操纵的人
Senator Corleone. Governor Corleone. Something.
柯里昂参议员
柯里昂州长之类的
再建立一个王国
Another pezzo da novanta.
Well...
这个…
Just wasn't enough time, Michael. Wasn't enough time.
时间不多了，麦克 时间不多了
We'll get there, Pop. We'll get there.
我们会做到的，爸
我们会做到的
Now listen, whoever comes to you with this Barzini meeting,
你听好…
谁请你去和巴西尼开会
他就是叛徒
he's the traitor. Don't forget that.
千万别忘了
Can I hold it, please?
能让我拿吗？
我能自己浇水
- Can I water these? - Yes, go ahead.
我可以浇水吗？
可以，浇吧！
Over here, over here.
这里，来这里
Be careful. You're spilling it.
小心点，别溅到了，小心
Antony!
安东尼，过来，来吧…
Come here, come here.
来这里
That's it. We'll put it right there.
对了，放在这
I'll show you something. Come here.
来，有东西给你看
来这
Stand there.
你站好
Give me an orange!
把柳丁给我
别怕
That's a new trick.
这是新把戏
You run in there. Run in there.
你去里面，去里面
Where are you?
你在哪？
倒下去
Mike, can I have a minute?
麦克，能借一步说话吗？
巴西尼想要安排一次会议
Barzini wants to arrange a meeting.
他说任何的问题
He says we can straighten out any of our problems.
都可以谈出一个解决之道
- You talked to him? - Yeah.
-你和他谈过了？ -是的
我能安排安全事宜
I can arrange security. On my territory.
在我的地盘上，好吗？
- All right? - All right.
-好的 -好！
Do you know how they're going to come at you?
你知道他们预备 怎么对付你吗？
They're arranging a meeting in Brooklyn. Tessio's ground.
他们安排在布鲁克林开会
泰西欧的地盘上
Where I'll be safe.
说在那我会安全的
I always thought it would be Clemenza, not Tessio.
我一直以为是克里曼沙 没想到是泰西欧
It's the smart move. Tessio was always smarter.
这一招漂亮，泰西欧一向聪明
But I'm going to wait.
但我会静观其变
After the baptism.
等洗礼过了再说
I've decided to be godfather to Connie's baby.
我决定当康妮小孩的教父了
And then I'll meet with Don Barzini
然后我再去见巴西尼
and Tattaglia. All the heads of the five families.
还有塔塔基利亚
所有五大家族的族长
（意大利文祷词）
阿门
麦克，你相信上帝吗？
Michael, do you believe in God, the Father, Creator of Heaven and Earth?
全能的天父，万物的创造者
I do.
我相信
Do you believe in Jesus Christ, His only Son, our Lord?
你相信耶稣基督 他的独子，我们的主吗？
我相信
I do.
你相信圣灵，神圣的教堂吗？
Do you believe in the Holy Ghost, the Holy Catholic Church?
我相信
I do.
（意大利文祷词）
麦克柯里昂
Michael Francis Rizzi, do you renounce Satan?
你弃绝撒旦吗？
I do renounce him.
我弃绝
And all his works?
包括他所有的作为吗？
I do renounce them.
我弃绝
Oh, God!
- And all his pomps? - I do renounce them.
包括他所有的虚伪？
我弃绝
Michael Rizzi, will you be baptised?
麦克柯里昂
你愿意当他的教父吗？
我愿意
I will.
（意大利文祷词）
Michael Rizzi, go in peace, and may the Lord be with you. Amen.
麦克柯里昂
愿主与你同在，阿门
凯
Kay!
Kiss your godfather.
这是你的教父！
Can't go to Vegas. Something's come up. Everybody has to leave without us.
卡洛
我现在不能去拉斯维加斯
临时有要事，让他们先走吧！
- Mike, it's our first vacation! - Connie, please.
-麦克，这是我们第一次度假 -康妮，别吵
-你要我怎么做 -回家去等我电话，有要事
Go back to the house, wait for my call. It's important.
好的
我只需一两天
I'll only be a couple of days.
旅途愉快，妈
We're on our way to Brooklyn.
我们要去布鲁克林了
- I hope Mike can get us a good deal. - I'm sure he will.
我希望麦克今晚能谈个好交易
他一定会的
Sal, Tom, the boss says he'll come in a separate car, so you two go on ahead.
沙尔、汤姆
老板说他自己坐车来
叫你们先走
他不能那么做
- That screws up my arrangements. - That's what he said.
-弄乱了我所有的安排 -他是这么说的
I can't go either, Sal.
我也不能去，沙尔
Tell Mike it was only business. I always liked him.
告诉麦克这纯粹是生意
我一直都喜欢他
他会了解的，沙尔
- He understands that. - Excuse me, Sal.
抱歉了，沙尔
Tom, can you get me off the hook?
汤姆，能替我求个情吗？
- For old times' sake? - Can't do it, Sally.
-看在老交情的份上 -我做不到，沙尔
You have to answer for Santino, Carlo.
你得为山尼的事偿命，卡洛
- Mike, you got it all wrong. - You fingered Sonny for Barzini.
-你误会了，麦克 -你为巴西尼的人设计害山尼
That little farce you played with my sister.
你和我姐姐演的那场闹剧
- You think that could fool a Corleone? - I'm innocent. I swear on the kids.
以为骗得过柯里昂家的人吗？
麦克，我是清白的
我以我的孩子来发誓
-求你，麦克，别这样对我 -坐下
- Please, don't do this. - Sit down.
Don't do this to me, please.
麦克，别这样对我，求你
Barzini is dead.
巴西尼死了！
So is Philip Tattaglia.
菲立浦塔塔基利亚也死了
Moe Greene.
还有莫格林、史特基 克里安诺
Strachi. Cuneo.
今天我一次清理整个家族的事
Today I settle all family business, so don't tell me you're innocent, Carlo.
所以别跟我说你是无辜的 卡洛
Admit what you did.
承认你所做过的
Get him a drink.
给他一杯酒
Come on.
说吧！
Don't be afraid, Carlo. Do you think I'd make my sister a widow?
别怕，卡洛
你以为我忍心 让我姐姐当寡妇？
I'm godfather to your son, Carlo.
我又是你儿子的教父，卡洛
Go ahead, drink, drink.
喝吧！…
No, you're out of the family business. That's your punishment.
卡洛，从此你退出家族的生意 这是给你的惩罚
You're finished. I'm putting you on a plane to Vegas.
你玩完了 我送你上飞机去拉斯维加斯
Tom.
汤姆
I want you to stay there. Understand?
我要你留在那边，明白吗？
Only don't tell me you're innocent.
只是别告诉我你是无辜的
Because it insults my intelligence. Makes me very angry.
因为那等于把我当傻瓜
会让我非常生气
Who approached you?
现在，是谁和你接头的？
Tattaglia or Barzini?
塔塔基利亚还是巴西尼？
It was Barzini.
是巴西尼
Good.
好
There's a car waiting outside to take you to the airport.
外面有辆车等着送你去机场
I'll call your wife and tell her what flight you're on.
我通知你太太说你坐那班飞机
- Mike... - Get out of my sight.
-麦克，我… -快走，别让我看到你
Hello, Carlo.
卡洛
你想告诉我什么？
- I'm trying to tell you... - Mama, please!
-我想告诉你… -妈妈，拜托…
Michael!
麦克！…
- What is it? - Where is he?
-怎么了？ -他在哪儿？麦克
Michael, you lousy bastard! You killed my husband.
麦克，你这混蛋 你杀了我丈夫
你看爸一死，就没人能管你了
You waited until Papa died, so nobody could stop you.
所以你就把他杀了
你一直把山尼的死怪在他身上
You blamed him for Sonny. Everybody did.
你一直如此，大家都如此
但你有没有想过我？
But you never thought about me! Now what are we going to do?
从来不在乎我
我以后要怎么办？
Connie.
康妮…
Why do you think he kept Carlo at the Mall? He knew he was going to kill him.
你以为他为何要卡洛在他身边
他早就算计好要杀他
And you stood godfather to our baby. You lousy cold-hearted bastard!
你还是我孩子的教父
你这个冷酷的混蛋
Want to know how many men he had killed with Carlo? Read the papers!
你知道除了卡洛 他还杀过多少人吗？
看看报纸吧！…
是你丈夫…
That's your husband, that's your husband!
No! No, no...
不要！…
Take her upstairs. Get her a doctor.
带她上楼
找医生来
She's hysterical.
她神经错乱了
Hysterical.
歇斯底里
Michael, is it true?
麦克，是真的吗？
- Don't ask me about my business, Kay. - Is it true?
-我跟你说过别管公事，凯 -是真的吗？
Don't ask me about my business. Enough!
别过问我的公事
-不！ -够了
All right.
好吧！
This one time.
只此一次
This one time I'll let you ask me about my affairs.
这次我让你问吧！
Is it true?
是真的吗？
Is it?
No.
不是
I guess we both need a drink. Come on.
我想我们两个都需要喝一杯
我去倒
Don Corleone.
柯里昂阁下